<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schemas/ddhi_oht.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
    <titleStmt>
      <title>Transcription of an interview with <persName>Charles G. Billo</persName></title>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
      <p>Dartmouth College Oral History Program</p>
      <p>The Dartmouth Vietnam Project</p>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <recordingStmt>
        <recording type="audio">
          <date from-iso="2015-08-14" to-iso="2015-08-15"/>
        </recording>
      </recordingStmt>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <particDesc>
      <listPerson>
        <person xml:id="dim" role="interviewer">
          <persName>Chileta Dim</persName>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="billo" role="interviewee">
          <persName>Charles G. Billo</persName>
        </person>
      </listPerson>
    </particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <p>Converted from docx-formatted transcription of recorded
    interview with pandoc 2.7.3</p>
    <p>Transcribed by Mim Eisenberg/WordCraft</p>
  </encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
  

<u who="#dim">This is Chileta Dim, and I’m here with Charles [G.] Billo at the
Dartmouth Special Collections Library at Rauner Library [sic; Rauner
Special Collections Library] in Hanover, New Hampshire. It’s August
14^th^, 2015, and right now it’s about 1:15.

So first off, thank you so much for joining us, Charlie.</u>

<u who="#billo">My pleasure</u>

<u who="#dim">I hope this comes to great fruit. So let’s just start at the very
beginning. When were you born?</u>

<u who="#billo">I was born in October 1942 in Bronxville, New York, a suburb of
New York City.</u>

<u who="#dim">And what was it like living in that area of the city? World War II
was just coming to an end. Do you have any recollection?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, my earliest memories are from 1947. I do recall, however,
that my father participated in the U.S. Navy as a doctor in World War
II, and I recall him coming home in his uniform and talking about his
experiences in France.</u>

<u who="#dim">What was that like, having your father in the military, in a major
war and growing up with those stories in your house?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, he was always—modestly pointed out that he was in
D-Day-Plus-10. He wasn’t trying to pretend that he was in the D-Day
invasion. And his job on the beaches was to sort out or triage the
injured infantrymen and decide which ones could be treated locally and
which ones should be put on a boat back to England.

Of course, he was able to travel in his off days, in France, and brought
back some memorabilia, which I still have, about—that he had picked up
from captured Nazi installations. He had nothing but respect for the
guts of the infantrymen who stormed those beaches.

So that was the atmosphere that I grew up in, which was one of service
to the country, not shirking and doing the right, patriotic thing. And
that—later on, in the ’60s, those lessons were quite important to me.</u>

<u who="#dim">With all that going on with your father in the house, was military
service something that you thought of early on?</u>

<u who="#billo">No, my father wanted me to be a doctor, and that was the end of
the story.</u>

<u who="#dim">It often is.

So tell me a little bit about your mother. What was her name?</u>

<u who="#billo">My mother. Barbara Leggett Billo, a Wellesley [College] grad.</u>

<u who="#dim">What was her maiden name?</u>

<u who="#billo">Barbara Leggett.</u>

<u who="#dim">Leggett.</u>

<u who="#billo">But she was a traditional 1950s homemaker. She helped raise me
and my two sisters and supported my father, who had a very active
pediatric practice in my home town and needed backstopping because of
his very long hours.</u>

<u who="#dim">So what was it like living in your neighborhood? What kind of town
was it? What kind of atmosphere was it for children?</u>

<u who="#billo">It was a wonderful atmosphere for children. It was very safe. It
was a town that was definitely upper middle class. A lot of corporate
CEOs lived there. It was probably a predominantly Republican town, and I
attended Bronxville schools from kindergarten all the way through high
school. And [it] was a wonderful time and place to grow up, although
later on, one discovers that it was a kind of protected life that we led
and a very privileged life.

When I got to college, my adviser, who knew Bronxville schools, pointed
out that essentially I went to a high-quality—what amounted to a
high-quality private school, like a boarding school. Of course, when
you’re a student, you get up in the morning and just go off to school.
You don’t think about the privileges that we had and the type of
education and advantages that we all received there.</u>

<u who="#dim">So mentioning how privileged and protected that you felt your
neighborhood was, what was _your_ interaction with the rest of the city?</u>

<u who="#billo">You mean New York City?</u>

<u who="#dim">Right.</u>

<u who="#billo">It was very limited and sporadic in those days. We’re talking
about the 1950s. My parents went out of their way to expose us to the
cultural advantages of New York: the Hayden Planetarium, the museums,
the Metropolitan Opera. The train into New York City from my home town
was a 30-minute ride, and when I got older, I went into town, into New
York City on my own, occasionally with my buddies when we were in high
school. We went to—we really lived large and went to various concerts,
rock ’n’ roll concerts, but that was when I was a junior or senior in
high school. But prior to that, it was more along the lines of what I
was saying, which was visiting cultural spots.

My grandma on my mother’s side lived in Brooklyn, New York. We would
drive to Brooklyn every couple of weeks and have Sunday dinner with her.
I remember passing the ships, the transatlantic ocean liners as we drove
along the West Side Highway in the 1950s. There were a series of major
ocean liners docked at a series of piers, and that was all very romantic
and exciting. And we’d read the names of the various ships and exotic
Scandinavian and Dutch and other names. So that, I remember distinctly.</u>

<u who="#dim">So did that instill in you any sort of desire for travel or any
sort of relation-want of outside the U.S.?</u>

<u who="#billo">To a degree. One doesn’t really draw a straight line on that kind
of thing when you’re 10, 11, 12, but suppose in the back of my mind,
there was always at some level, as I grew older, some curiosity about
the wider world. And my parents, of course, encouraged us to learn
foreign languages, encouraged us to think big about the world.

When I was a junior in high school, I was chosen to go to Italy on the
American Field Service exchange student program, and so we actually took
a ship from New York to Rotterdam (the Netherlands), which—when you’re
16 years old, you’re on a student ship. It was one of the most exciting,
challenging things I’d done up till that point in my life.</u>

<u who="#dim">We’ll probably return to that a little bit later, but you say “us.”
Did you have siblings?</u>

<u who="#billo">I had—I have two sisters, one older, a couple of years older, who
lives in Richmond, Virginia, and the other is about five years younger,
and she lives in Dorset, Vermont.</u>

<u who="#dim">So did you—were you three close? What sort of relationship did you
have, especially?</u>

<u who="#billo">I’d say we were reasonably close. One advantage that we had was
we always vacationed together, growing up. We either went to—near Cape
Cod in the summer for a week or two or we went to northern Vermont, the
Northeast Kingdom of Vermont. And so we were a very tightly knit family,
and my parents were very active in making sure that we understood the
importance of family. Of course, like any other American family, there
were always periodic rivalries and siblings disagreements. <vocal><desc>Chuckles.</desc></vocal></u>

<u who="#dim">So let’s make our way up to starting school, kindergarten. You’re
probably around five. What sort of transition was school for you? What
was the elementary school experience like, if you have any remembrance
of that?</u>

<u who="#billo">I have all good memories of that. I mean, I can’t give you a
whole lot of detail, but I went to a school that—for example, in high
school there were only a hundred kids in the grade, and so you can
imagine, in elementary school or in kindergarten, we were only talking,
if I remember correctly, 15 kids in a classroom.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mmm.</u>

<u who="#billo">The other part that I didn’t mention was that there was
practically zero diversity in Bronxville, New York, just by the nature
of the economy and that type of—the cost of living and et cetera, et
cetera. So my recollection of that period that you asked me about was
one of sitting in a classroom with all white children, a white teacher,
very atypical of the wider world that was waiting for me out there.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mm-hm. Did you have—so this period probably extends all the way up
into the later ’50s. Any recollection of the beginning of the civil
rights movement or anything in the news at the time?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yes. Of course, we paid attention to the news every day. We read
the newspapers every day. But we were in our own silo, so it had no
immediate import as a youngster, for my day-to-day life. I will
remember—I will say, and I’m not sure about cause and effect, but my
parents raised us to be respectful of all races and all ethnic
backgrounds, and I remember—because I was actively involved in sports, I
participated in a lot of sports that involved diverse groups, and I
remember that I always—even though I led—I was living in this totally
unrealistic kind of a cocoon, we always had respect for anyone who was
different, who looked different or—because that was the way we were
brought up.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you so much.

Do you have any recollection about when you started high school?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, yeah, I’ve got a lot of recollections.</u>

<u who="#dim">I mean about what year did you start high school?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. That would have been in about 1957, give or take.</u>

<u who="#dim">Fifty-seven.</u>

<u who="#billo">I will say that up until ’57, I sometimes was a somewhat
rebellious student, and I was seeking acceptance among my peers. I
misbehaved somewhat. My parents decided to take things in hand. They
weren’t happy with the trajectory I was on, and they sent me to Phillips
Academy Andover summer school, which was a transformative experience for
me.</u>

<u who="#dim">Do you know what year that was?</u>

<u who="#billo">It was roughly the summer of 1957. The thing about that was
twofold: One was that I met teachers who were very both athletic and
intelligent. For me, this was extremely important, that I have male
mentors or role models who I expected. It’s what perhaps I hadn’t found
in middle school, which I was always cutting up. And there were some
teachers at Andover that turned me around. And then in hindsight, later
on, I came to realize that my parents were doing me a favor, or showing
they cared about me enough to pay the money to send me to that school,
and so I realized that I had a good thing going.</u>

<u who="#dim">It’s wonderful to meet older people who care and really believe in
you.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. Of course, when you’re in ninth grade, you don’t—you don’t
process that. At the time, my take-away was, _Oh, my God, I have to
leave my buddies at home to go to [.underline]#that# place?_ But it was
only later that—when I had my own kids, that it became clear that they
cared about me, and so that was—that was transformative for me.</u>

<u who="#dim">Was there anyone in particular that stood out? Any names you
remember?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, in particular, a math teacher, algebra teacher named Mr.
[Thomas M.] Mikula [pronounced MIH-coo-luh]. It was a Finnish name.

DIM:` Can you spell that?</u>

<u who="#billo">Sorry?</u>

<u who="#dim">Could you spell it?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, M-i-k-u-l-a. I may not be giving it the proper Finnish
pronunciation. I think we called him mih-COO-luh, Mr. mih-COO-luh. He
was an ex-[U.S.] Marine and the wrestling coach. And I wasn’t going to
mess with that guy. He taught me to stand up and take my medicine, and I
came out at the end of a summer—after a long struggle, I came out with a
pretty darn good grade in algebra. So that’s one memory I have.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you so much for sharing.

You mentioned a little earlier in the interview about rock concerts with
buddies in New York City? What was your friend group like? Did it change
after that summer?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, most of my friends derived from sports teams in high
school. I was a three-sport athlete.</u>

<u who="#dim">Wow.</u>

<u who="#billo">In a very small school, as I said, with only a hundred students
per grade, so a couple of these guys had this thought to go to the RKO
[Hamilton] Theater in Harlem, where [Albert J.] “Alan” Freed, the king
[sic; father] of rock ’n’ roll, was emceeing a concert, and Jerry Lee
Lewis was there. I can’t remember now the other performers. But for a
Bronxville kid to get on the train and risk going to a rock ’n’ roll
concert—I think it was in the daytime (I don’t want to overdramatize
this thing)—but for Charlie Billo, that was—I don’t even know if I told
my parents we were going. That was a high-risk venture.</u>

<u who="#dim">Were these common occurrences?</u>

<u who="#billo">No, no, it was seldom. But essentially in high school I was into
sports, and I played soccer, basketball and baseball, and I had some
good luck. I told you I won the scholarship to go to Italy. We lived
with an Italian family that I still keep in touch with. It was a good
time, but I had a lot of maturing to do, a lot of maturing to do.</u>

<u who="#dim">Well, if we can go back to the American Field Service trip that you
mentioned, going to Italy, what was that application process like? How
did you hear about it?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, American Field Service then, and probably still today, was
the preeminent high school exchange student program, and our school
traditionally hosted a couple of visiting scholarship students. And they
would live with a Bronxville family for the whole school year. And, on
the other side, the two or three Bronxville kids every year were awarded
scholarships to go abroad. So my year, I went to Italy, and a colleague
of mine went to Indonesia, and a third colleague went to New Zealand, so
that was quite something.

The part about my experience was that I was there in the summer, so I
was not attending classes in Italy, and the only Italian language
training I had was on the ship going over. It was a seven- or eight-day
voyage, and every morning we’d meet on deck, those of us that were
headed to Italy, and we were boning up on Italian. It was pretty
primitive, but that was as much as I understood of the language.

So American Field Service is a great program. It’s branched out
considerably since the 1950s.</u>

<u who="#dim">Branched out in what way?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, for one thing, they send a lot more Americans to developing
countries than they did in my day. I don’t have specifics to back up
that assertion, but I think, in my day, it was a fairly elite operation,
and today it’s probably in every—the American Field Service may be
active in every school—I don’t know—on the East Coast or across into
California. I just haven’t been tracking it. But it’s a prestigious
organization.</u>

<u who="#dim">And what year was all this?</u>

<u who="#billo">That would have been the summer of ’59 I went to Italy, just
before my senior year. It opened up experiences and exposure to
different settings and operating away from my family, so it came at an
important time, as I entered my senior year in high school. Yeah, it
was—it also involved, when I got back, making a lot of speeches and trip
reports and slide shows, the usual stuff you do in high school to share
with your classmates and underclassmen. So that was a very, very lucky
break.

The family they matched me up with in Turin, which is the Detroit of
Italy—it’s where the Fiat automobile cars used to be made—was—in terms
of socioeconomic status, was similar to Bronxville, and that’s how the
organization worked. They tried to match up students in America with
sort of similar situations overseas so that if you’re living in a
family, you have to have some basic compatibility to make the family
structure work, and I guess that was the motivation.

So the father in my Italian family was head of the manufacturing
association. Would be like the National Association of Manufacturers in
the United States, definitely a conservative business organization. And
they were able to—because of their status, they were able to share with
me a lot of different experiences: weekends in the Alps, side trips to
Venice. So, yeah, it was a very successful experience for me and one
that I cherish, and I still, as I said, keep in touch with those of the
family that are still living.

And when I went into the State Department [sic; U.S. Department of
State], I went back to Italy following [the] Vietnam [War], and now I’m
an Italian teacher on the side here in Hanover. So it all—in the end, it
all circles back, in one sense or another.</u>

<u who="#dim">So that’s the summer before you enter your senior year.</u>

<u who="#billo">Right.</u>

<u who="#dim">Senior year of high school, what were you thinking post graduation?
What was the college application process like?</u>

<u who="#billo">The long and the short of it was that my parents had gone to
prestigious schools in New England, so there was no talk of me doing
anything but going to prestigious schools in New England.</u>

<u who="#dim">Were they alumni? Your mother was from Wellesley.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. My father went to Williams College. And so probably some of
my teachers and counselors in high school realized that maybe a highly
competitive college wasn’t the best suited for me, that I was somewhat
shy, and they were tossing out ideas, and, to make a long story short,
there was only one possible opportunity for me, and that was to go to
some Ivy League school full stop. I ended up going to Brown University.
That was an interesting experience, in more ways than one, but—so that
was that.

I was—I was—in high school, I was captain of this team and captain of
that team, and I was president of my class, and I—if I respected a
teacher, I went full bore, you know, on the subject matter. I had a
couple of mentors in high school. If I disrespected the teacher, I
wouldn’t work hard, and so that was—that was essentially—the whole
backdrop beneath all that was essentially a person who was too easily
influenced by my parents, who maybe wasn’t ripe for the real world away
from home and who—to get ahead in school, I had to work hard. I wasn’t
one of these folks where anything came easy.

So in all of that mix, I wound up as a freshman at Brown University and
played varsity soccer at Brown and failed to achieve much in pre-med
studies, and that was—that was, in a nutshell, my experience at college,
not being focused on a career, not knowing—not being hell bent for a
particular career, just working on improving my social skills and
fraternity life and being one of the guys. So it was an interesting
time.</u>

<u who="#dim">What year did you matriculate?</u>

<u who="#billo">Nineteen sixty, fall of 1960.</u>

<u who="#dim">So that was the year [President John F.] Kennedy was elected. Did
you have any perceptions of that? How was the campus reacting to that
campaign?</u>

<u who="#billo">That’s a good question. Probably guys that I knew on campus were
Democrats and very open to Kennedy and the New Frontier. I, having grown
up in Bronxville as a Republican, in a Republican family, I was often
just repeating various mantras that Republicans had at the time about
the Kennedys. And so that was—yeah. I mean, I can’t—to be honest, I
can’t remember what the undergraduate body was doing or thinking when
Kennedy was elected. I would just say they were probably tilting towards
supporting the Democrats, and people—that’s what I remember right now.

I was apolitical. I wasn’t one to get out and campaign for candidates.
Yeah. It’s an interesting question that you pose in that later on, when
I joined the [U.S.] Foreign Service, I would explain to my cohort of
friends and my peers, my parents’ friends that Kennedy said, “Ask not
what your country can do for you.” I was in this mode of—at least I
adopted this posture of, “Hey, these guys on the New Frontier were the
type of people I looked for growing up, the people that were both smart
and athletic.” And I could sit here and name several of Kennedy’s
advisers that met this criterion.</u>

<u who="#dim">Any in particular that you looked up to?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, there was a law professor at Columbia University named
Richard [N.] Gardner, who was a mentor of mine when I went to graduate
school. He was a Rhodes Scholar. So in one way or another—maybe this
was, like, an ex post facto rationale—I signed onto the New Frontier,
idealistic wave that by then, a lot of young Americans were into. And so
this was—this was a feel-good kind of a thing. And get some direction in
my life and have it sort of validated by these hotshots down in
Washington[, D.C.].</u>

<u who="#dim">So you mentioned briefly before that you joined a fraternity? What
year was that?</u>

<u who="#billo">It was when I was a sophomore at Brown. We had a lot of soccer
players and lacrosse players, and we—we weren’t the goody-goody student
council president type of group. On the other hand, we weren’t as
degenerate as some of the other fraternities. It was a good—a good
experience. We knew how to throw a party. I still keep in touch with a
couple of my colleagues. It was a good time. It was all about Charlie
Billo learning—working on his social skills and gaining some confidence.</u>

<u who="#dim">And so how was soccer life for you? Since you’ve been involved in
team sports since you were a child, was that a major factor in your—and
you were a varsity soccer player in college. How did that affect your
experience?</u>

<u who="#billo">That’s a good question in that when you arrive—I think when a lot
of people arrive as a freshman, you’re scared as heck. It’s all
different. You don’t know anyone. So I had an immediate nucleus of
friends who were teammates, so even if, you know, nowhere else, at least
I had this nucleus of support, so you can gauge: _Hey, am I as good as
these guys? Am I as smart as these guys? Am I prepared the right way?_
You know, you can test yourself. And that was as huge lift for me,
having that. I don’t what other—if I hadn’t had that, it’s hard to
figure out where or how I would have landed on my feet.

This is not relevant, but we had a very successful soccer team. That
always helps, too. And we got in some travel every second year. We’d be
up here in Hanover, playing Dartmouth. And we held our own in soccer. We
got totally trounced in football. In those days, soccer was at 11 on
Saturday morning; football was around 1:30, so after our soccer game,
before going home, we had to go and endure watching Dartmouth just walk
all over the Brown football team. Those were difficult times.

But we—as I said, every second year, you were traveling to an away game,
and so we’d be in—down at Harvard or over at Columbia or—yeah, so that’s
cool, you know, when you’re 20 years old.</u>

<u who="#dim">And so, in just sort of describing your school life, it seems that
you went along collecting mentors, collecting friends, building your
social capacities. Post graduation, did you keep in contact with a lot
of these people? You mentioned some, but—</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, yeah, very much, yeah. A bunch of us went down to New York
after college. I was at Columbia Business School, and we had a good—we
just picked up in New York where we left off in—at Brown. Mentors. Yeah,
I had these high school teachers at Bronxville, a couple of them that I
really respected, and I would look them up and try to—try to keep those
flames going. Yeah, I—it’s not much to really comment on other than the
obvious. I think going to New York City and going to Columbia
University, you realize it’s a much bigger stage than anything I’d
experienced in college. And so I—I mean, Columbia University, then and
now, was a world-class institution, you know, in the sciences. And New
York City is a world-class city. So I was—I was into enjoying all the
delights of New York.

I burned through my father’s money, tuition money, and so in the end, I
picked up additional mentors that helped me navigate the next chapter,
and—yeah, it was—it was kind of a not very efficient way to proceed. And
there was a lot of waste and a lot of false starts, but I guess it’s—in
some way, it’s a journey, and you can’t pre-script these things.

Just to show you the kind of indecision that gripped me, when I was
leaving Brown, I knew I had no plan. I didn’t know what the plan was for
post graduation, so I applied to Navy OCS [Officer Candidate School],
which in those days was a proper avenue or a proper thing for an Ivy
League grad, or any grad, to do: go down to Navy OCS at Newport, Rhode
Island, under go the four months’ training, and then spend three years
in the U.S. Navy. This would have been in 1964.

Vietnam was not always on the front pages of the newspaper, and the
pressures were a lot different in ’64 than they were in ’66. So—and
then, miraculously, I was accepted at Columbia Business School, so I
told the Navy folks that I wouldn’t be joining them after all, so that
was a—that was a fork in the road for me. And in some level, it showed I
was essentially without any firm direction, and it was kind of
rudderless. You know, one could say I was grasping for straws. So, yeah,
it’s one of those unknowns you’ll never know. If I’d gone to Newport,
Rhode Island, and served in the Navy, how I would have developed. One
will never know.</u>

<u who="#dim">It’s a tough choice, sure.</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, in those days it as an honorable thing to do. I mean, not
to repeat myself, in those days—this comes out in the Class of 1964 book
on Vietnam that was published here at Dartmouth, how many of those
authors said they either were in ROTC or they went to Navy Officer
Candidate School, because it was an honorable thing to do, especially if
your dad had served, you know, and it was in your family fabric.</u>

<u who="#dim">So you decided to go to Columbia Business School. Tough choice.
What did you major in in undergrad? Did that transfer to Columbia at
all?</u>

<u who="#billo">Not immediately. I was a history major, which was a smart move.
Brown had an excellent history department, and European history was my
main interest. It didn’t really play into the business school at all,
but I learned when I got down there that the—Columbia had what they
called a joint degree program, or dual degree program with the Columbia
School of International Relations [sic; Columbia University's School of
International Affairs, now Columbia University's School of International
and Public Affairs]. And I argued or persuaded my way into that, so I
ended up getting the MBA degree in about, let’s say, ’66, roughly. And
then started working on another master’s degree in the School of
International Relations. And that was where history and that kid of
thing played an important role. That was cool.

And at the School of International Relations, that’s where I found these
other mentors. I’ve mentioned law professor Richard Gardner. I also took
a course with Professor Roger Hilsman [Jr.], who had played a critical
role in the Kennedy administration with regard to Vietnam coup d’état
against President [Ngô Đình] Diệm. I got to confess, for the record,
that as a 22-year-old student, I was sort of taken by Roger Hilsman.
Roger Hilsman was a [U.S. Military Academy at] West Point grad. Got a
doctorate at Yale [University]. Was a very assertive, self-confident guy
who’d served in the New Frontier, and he was—I had no reason to be
skeptical about him.

In fact, one time I called on him at his office, just because I wanted
to have a chat with him about this, that or the other thing, and he
said, “Well, what are you gonna do when you get outta here?” I said, “I
want to join the State Department.” And he looked at me and said, “Oh,
you mean the Foreign Service.” Because he was a political appointee, so
those guys don’t join the Foreign Service; they join the “State
Department.” So I was sort of learning the lingo, and what it was that I
wanted to do was take the Foreign Service exam and join the Foreign
Service.

It was only later that I found out—Roger Hilsman had been fired by LBJ
[President Lyndon B. Johnson] and had washed up on the campus at
Columbia University and was busy writing a memoir about his experience
in the Kennedy administration. It’s called _To Move a Nation[: The
Politics of Foreign Policy in the Administration of John F. Kennedy]_.
And he was basically persona non grata around Democratic circles in
the—especially in the Johnson administration.

So that shows you <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>—you have to be a little more worldly wise
and savvy sometimes in one’s ambition to get ahead. You have to know
exactly what you’re doing and who you’re dealing with, and that’s a
whole chapter that we can spend time on later on, but—

So I loved the School of International Affairs. It was like taking all
the courses you always wanted to take in American foreign policy, in
economics, in European history. I mean, what’s not to like about that?
And they even organized a trip, a study trip to the U.N. [United
Nations] facilities in Europe—for example, the U.N. office in Geneva
[Switzerland] in the summer. A few of us were selected to take this
trip, and the Columbia University could open doors to very prominent
people in these big organizations, at NATO [North Atlantic Treaty
Organization] and—yeah that was—those were heady times for me.

But that always begged the question: _Well, what the heck are you gonna
do with all these degrees, and who’s gonna pay the bills?_ That was
always the looming question out there.
</u>

<incident><desc>Recording interruption.</desc></incident>

<u who="#dim">So we’re back after a short, one-minute break, and we’ll start off
with maybe going back to Professor Roger Hilsman and what your
relationship with him was like, and how did that feel, interacting with
such a prominent figure?</u>

<u who="#billo">Roger Hilsman taught a large lecture course at Columbia School
of International Relations. He was a specialist on Southeast Asia. He
had been a participant in Merrill’s Marauders [5307^th^ Composite Unit
(Provisional)] in World War II in Burma [now Myanmar]. He loved to talk
war stories, and he was very opinionated. And I vaguely remember his
lectures on Laos and the neutrality negotiations on Laos. This would
have been in—these lectures took place in 1966, ’67 period.

I remember him talking about Vietnam and about how the prosecute the
Vietnam War. He had strong views. He came across as a very
self-confident—and I gave him the benefit of the doubt, that he, as a
former operative in Burma, knew something about jungle warfare, and as a
West Post grad he certainly had the training to be credible. There were
some occasions when there’d be an ugly story in the newspaper referring
to the fact that Roger Hilsman was persona non grata in the Johnson
administration, and he always—when asked about it, he’d deflect those
stories, and he’d maintain this kind of confident air that he was in
charge and he knew better.

It turned out, as the history books show and the Pentagon Papers
["Report of the Office of the Secretary of Defense Vietnam Task Force"]
reveal, that Hilsman was instrumental in approving a rash telegram that
was sent to Ambassador [Henry Cabot] Lodge [Jr.] in Saigon in November
of 1963—it was either October or November of ’63—essentially giving
Lodge and the U.S. mission the green light to back a coup d’état against
President Diệm. And this, the history books will show, was a pivotal
moment in our involvement in the Vietnam War. And following Diệm’s
murder by the coup plotters, the Vietnamese government never regained
any kind of political unity or momentum, which only sapped any efforts
that we had to counter the challenge of the North Vietnamese.

So this is all well-documented material. It’s just ironic that I
crossed paths with Professor Hilsman, and it was something that’s still
vividly etched in my mind after all these years.</u>

<u who="#dim">So you mentioned your time at Columbia was between ’66 and ’67,
and we’re amping up our involvement in Vietnam. Protests are amping up.
What was the sense on campus, in New York City or just within you,
yourself, with the war and a lot of the animosity, especially among
students, towards the war?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, that’s an interesting question. Yeah, the war was more and
more prominently treated on the evening news. By then there were several
correspondents from each of the television networks on the ground in
Vietnam, and so if one were a student or any aware person in our
society, you were shown very graphic images of fighting and operations
in Vietnam. So it began to get very, very real.

At this time, a lot of the students had figured out that maybe the
Johnson administration was playing fast and loose with the facts, that
there was—LBJ’s personality led to a lot of deceptive behavior. The
journalists would uncover various deceptions. I’m thinking—for example,
just to pick one example, the Tonkin Gulf resolutions. And they—students
sensed that this thing wasn’t going well and that the administration was
not being totally honest. And, hey, guess what: Almost every male
student had a draft card and was susceptible to possible Selective
Service [System] draft notices coming in, especially when the big
buildups started in 1965, ’66, and the draft calls doubled.

At that point—you asked about the atmosphere at Columbia. There was a
lot of student organization against the Vietnam War, against the
administration. You could see it daily when you headed up to campus.
Students later on, I think, invaded some of the offices of the
professors and looked through their files. Columbia University was found
to have contracts with the government, like the Institute for Defense
Analyses. And this was like red meat for the antiwar people. This was
probably after I left Columbia, after I graduated, but they went after
the administration and the Columbia president, big time.

So, yeah, I would say, yeah, 1966, ’67 things were really amping up,
and it kind of—that being said, it kind of caught me by surprise, in the
sense that I left Columbia in May of ’67 and didn’t have any firm place
to go, so I was ripe for getting a letter from my draft board.

Yeah, it was—I had taken the Foreign Service exam in the spring of ’67,
and I passed it. That was the written exam. This all gets back to the
general vision I had of joining the Foreign Service and playing to my
skills as a political analyst and a linguist.

The next hurdle was I needed to pass the oral exam, and that was
scheduled for July of ’67. So, yeah, it was a confusing—to answer your
original question, it was a confusing time, and people were—one’s peers
were constantly bringing up the Selective Service System and, “Hey,
what’s your status?” And people were looking to extend at universities
in order to maintain their deferments.

And one of the ironies of some of this business relating to Selective
Service was that some people could obtain medical deferments because of
asthma or you name it, and a friend of mine pointed out later on that a
lot of the people who had been the biggest athletes and the toughest and
most self-confident young men turned out to have football injuries that
miraculously made them undraftable. And it was kind of a strange and
bizarre thing, so that you—the guys that one knew who were maybe nerdy
in school—they—I’m generalizing like crazy, but in some ironic way,
those guys might have been first in line to be drafted, and the people
who one would have imagined to be infantrymen got deferments because of
legitimate knee injuries, et cetera.</u>

<u who="#dim">Well, so you’re graduating Columbia in May of ’67? Your draft card
has not come up?</u>

<u who="#billo">Within a month, I got a letter from my local draft board, which
was in a neighboring town, Mount Vernon, New York, asking me: “Hi, Mr.
Billo. What are _you_ up to these days?” And I had to reply that I was
no longer in university, no longer in graduate school. So within a short
period—I can’t remember the details right now—they sent me a letter
inviting me to a pre-induction physical exam held in the Battery of New
York City, way downtown, in Manhattan. So that got my attention very
quickly.

Meanwhile, I was summoned to New York City to take the oral part of the
Foreign Service exam. I don’t know how, but I impressed these guys well
enough that I passed that, and so if the sequencing could work out, I
had a chance of avoiding the draft. And I’d already burned my bridges
with Navy OCS back in the spring of ’64, so—and so it was a very tense
few months there.

It turned out that I did go to Manhattan and have the pre-induction
physical. I was pronounced fit for military service. And that was in
October of ’67. And then I—at that point, I was straining to find out
when the Foreign Service would actually invite me to Washington to enter
the basic training program.

So without spinning this out in great depth, I told my draft board that
I had been approved by the Foreign Service and I was waiting any day to
go to Washington, and they—at a certain point in November of ’67, they
invited me to the draft board for a “meeting” of the draft board, which
was me and the three voting members, sitting at a table. Of course, in
those days—because you know that each draft board had to fulfill a
certain quota of numbers, and one never knew—like, my board was in Mount
Vernon. No one knew whether they were anywhere near fulfilling their
quotas.

This was—as I said earlier, the U.S. involvement in Vietnam was really
ramping up, so a person like me was prime bait. I went to this meeting
in Mount Vernon. There were three reps at the table. The clerk of the
draft board—this is after I had explained that I was seeking a deferment
because I was joining the government and I was going to be working
overseas, et cetera, et cetera, for the Department of State, that the
clerk of the draft board said, “I vote we draft this guy.”</u>

<u who="#dim">Wow.</u>

<u who="#billo">And the second person said, “Well, I don’t think so.” So it all
came down to this third individual, who was a businessman, local
businessman, who was a volunteer. It wasn’t his full-time job to be on
the draft board. He was older. It was around 12 noon. He was probably on
a lunch break, coming down. And I sensed he was a well educated man by
his demeanor. And he said, “Hold on. Wait a minute. I think this young
man could do more for our country working for the Department of State
than as a draftee.” And so the vote went down two to one against this
lady, the clerk who wanted to make sure that some Bronxville kid got on
the next train to Fort Dix. So that was—that made my day <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>, as
you can imagine.

They allowed me to proceed with this whole application to move to
Washington, and it turned out, a couple of weeks later I got a letter
from the Foreign Service, saying, “Please come to Washington on January
4, 1968, to enter this class. Your pay is $7,700 a year.” And then they
had some line to the effect of: “If you don’t believe that you can make
this date, please let us know.” <vocal><desc>Chuckles.</desc></vocal></u>

<u who="#dim">Little do they know.</u>

<u who="#billo"><vocal><desc>Laughs.</desc></vocal> So <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal> I was so thrilled to get this letter. I
was going to be there for that appointment in D.C. come hell or high
water. So the only reason I’m going through all this in this detail is
that—and it’s a fairly obvious thing for me to say—is that I was by no
means a war hero or any kind of a super patriotic, brave individual. As
you can tell from what I’ve just said, I was trying every stratagem to
forestall the draft and to find some other niche for myself, and so in
that respect and for the record, it has to be said that I was not any
different than a lot of folks in that era of my age, who joined Reserve
units, people like Senator [William W.] “Bill” Bradley, who had
connections and got into a Reserve unit, and countless others that I’m
not even going to attempt to name. I was—I was—I wanted no part of—of
joining the U.S. Army, and that’s all I have to say about that.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay. So you made it into the Foreign Service.</u>

<u who="#billo">I have to say, in just one footnote—</u>

<u who="#dim">Absolutely.</u>

<u who="#billo">—I experienced a lot of pain in this decision area because it
wasn’t in my family background or character or upbringing to run away
and go to Canada, like a lot of people in that era were doing, so I
was—I always felt a lot of stress, was the simplest way of putting it,
that I had to do the—do what was asked. I wasn’t going to be a deserter.
That was just not—not in the cards. No way. So, again, that’s a chapter
that one will never know how that might have played out, if I’d been
drafted and you know, what kind of—every person who’s in the [U.S.] Army
has a specialty. There’s a name for it, and I can’t remember what it is.
So not everyone in the Army is an infantryman, as you know.</u>

<u who="#dim">Right.</u>

<u who="#billo">And there are scores of other tasks and specialties that are
distributed, so—but as a youngster, you—you can’t—you can’t necessarily
see that. And so—yeah. So, again, I can’t—if I had been drafted, I don’t
know which of these specialties I might have followed, and blah, blah,
blah.

One thing for sure, though: I wasn’t going to be posted to West Germany
to defend the NATO frontier. That was for sure.</u>

<u who="#dim">So maybe along with that, how did your family react to you joining
the Foreign Service?</u>

<u who="#billo">They were okay with that. They understood that I had some
facility for foreign languages and that I had long since burned the
medical school bridge. But the part that they didn’t realize on January
of ’68 was that I was about to be assigned to the CORDS [Civil
Operations and Revolutionary Development Support] in Vietnam. So
that—that’s why I say they were pretty much okay with—you know, they
made their peace with it, that I’d be doing honorable work for the
United States, I’d be using a skill set that I had developed, that I
would be working with good people and that I was a young guy trying to
live the dream of John F. Kennedy. You know, “Ask not what your
country…” So I guess they made their peace with this idea.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay. So end of ’67, you made it into Foreign Service. When do you
begin your language training?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. Well, we had a two-month basic training course.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay.</u>

<u who="#billo">And there were some, let’s say, 40 people in my entering class.
And ten of us—at the end of the two months, they have a ceremony where
they announce your first assignment, and ten of us, including me, were
sent—were assigned to the CORDS program in Vietnam, Civil Operations for
[sic; and] Revolutionary Development Support. This was a program that
LBJ had endorsed. Was run by Robert [W.] Komer. The thrust of it
<vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>, as LBJ would have put it, was to send trained Americans out
into the field “to win the hearts and minds of the Vietnamese.” And
these Americans were also language capable, all to the good, because
they could pick up nuances of what was going on out in the provinces and
gain a better appreciation of where things stood and help the economic
development in the countryside, which was—you know, the counterpart to
the fighting war was the economic development and social development
side of the coin.</u>

<u who="#dim">So this is the beginning of ’68?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, this was March of ’68. So to answer your earlier question,
I started Vietnamese language training in April of ’68. It was six hours
a day, five days a week for ten months.</u>

<u who="#dim">Very intense.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. And it’s a tone language, as you know.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mm-hm.</u>

<u who="#billo">So it was something different than anything I’d ever
experienced. I mean, I have to say a couple things. First of all,
learning that I’d been assigned to the CORDS program was a total shock,
a jaw-dropping shock. I didn’t realize that that was even in the cards.
And my buddies, of course, from high school era, who had been following
my path, the whole graduate school business and then the foreign
service—they had sort of a good laugh at my expense, because I was going
to Vietnam anyway.

And the other thing I have to say right off the bat is that the Tet
Offensive took place in January of ’68, and I—even when I was in
graduate school at Columbia in ’66, ’67, I already had this intuitive
sense that things weren’t going well in Vietnam and that they had
revolving door governments after Diệm was assassinated. So even as early
as ’66, ’67, I was skeptical. And then come the Tet Offensive in ’68, I
lost all faith that this was an enterprise that was going anywhere. And
so I just want to say for the record that starting a ten-month language
course, I was by no means a true believer in this thing. You know, I—I
did what I was told.

I’d exhausted all my options at this stage. I’d only just <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>
managed to escape the clutches of the Mount Vernon, New York, draft
board, so that was fresh in my mind. I wasn’t going to defect to Canada,
and so it was a tricky, tricky time, you know, because you’re 22 years
old, 23, and you—intellectually you can’t really believe in what you’re
about to do in terms of a mission. Washington is in total chaos and
disarray because LBJ has announced that he’s not running for
reelection.</u>

<u who="#dim">That’s right.</u>

<u who="#billo">Martin Luther King Jr. is assassinated, and the—</u>

<u who="#dim">[Robert F.] “Bobby” Kennedy is assassinated.</u>

<u who="#billo">Bobby Kennedy in the summer, and then the antiwar people were
marching on the Pentagon, right, left and center, and getting arrested.
So that was the context in which I was embarking on this venture. It was
surreal. But so much of the whole coming years of my work was surreal,
so—

Anyway, I think I answered your question. I mean, we studied the
language in small groups of five or six students per teacher. The
teachers were native speakers. You learned sort of a lot about—through
the teachers, about the Vietnamese culture. Every once in a while,
they’d have “off- sites,” I guess or we’d be brief by military and other
folks about the policy in Vietnam.

We were given a few days’ training at Fort Bragg in North Carolina, to
learn how to handle weapons, like the M16 rifle.</u>

<u who="#dim">Oh, wow.</u>

<u who="#billo">And I went down there in May of ’68 to attend this so-called
training course.</u>

<u who="#dim">Can you explain for the recorder what you’re showing me?</u>

<u who="#billo">Oh. I have a certificate—(The Army is big into certificates. So
is the State Department, for that matter.)—that shows that I completed
the provincial senior adviser training course at the [U.S. Army] Special
Warfare School [now U.S. Army John F. Kennedy Special Warfare Center and
School] in Fort Bragg, North Carolina. As I recall, we were there for
four or five days. We received a lot of briefings by young captains
about what to expect when we got to Vietnam if we were going out to the
provinces. I don’t remember a whole lot of detail. They detonated a
couple of explosives near us, without telling us, to watch how high we
could jump off the bleachers. They were having fun with the civilians.
We were, like—I forget; let’s say a group of 20 or 30 civilians?

And we got to go to a firing range and fire M16 rifles, which were—that
was a very impressive weapon, and the bullets were easily four inches
long. And we were firing them at a distance of a couple hundred yards,
targets a couple hundred yards. I mean, it was—it was fun, from a macho
perspective, but by no means was any kind of training for actual,
potential combat duty or problems in Vietnam—I mean, I guess—I guess if
I’d come under some fire and someone had thrust a rifle in my hands, I
would have said, “Yeah! I know this thing. I’ve been here.” But it
was—it was sort of—I don’t know what the purpose of it was, really,
except to toughen us up in some level.</u>

<u who="#dim">So was this the extent of your weapons training? Basic training
for Foreign Service does not deal with any sort of combat?</u>

<u who="#billo">No. The Foreign Service, as I know you’re aware, staffs our
embassies in capitals all over the world, and our job is to defend
United States’ political interests vis-à-vis the host country, to
deliver policy papers to the host government, to persuade them of our
positions, and so—and then we write a lot of analytical reports on
conditions in the host country, economic reports, political reports,
make prognostications about which way the local government is likely to
go on a particular matter. So the whole Vietnam chapter was way, way out
of the traditional line of duty of a Foreign Service officer.

Parenthetically, lately, with the U.S. presence in Afghanistan in
particular, the Foreign Service was asked to send young men and women to
do provincial work in Afghanistan, at remote sites, so it was, in a way,
a replication of the CORDS program except this would have been in 2008
to—maybe even until today there are young Foreign Service people,
civilians out in the provinces of Afghanistan, trying to do political
and economic development work.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mmm. How everything just cycles back is incredible.

So here you are, getting foreign language training, and you mentioned
earlier that you grew up, most of undergrad, being relatively
apolitical, and then going to Columbia Business School and then the
International School, clearly getting more political background,
becoming more aware of what was happening, all the things that happened
in the mid ‘60s with the several assassinations and great political
turmoil. And then you enter into this military capacity that isn’t
direct combat, and you did mention that you didn’t—you didn’t really
believe in the war in Vietnam. But did you believe in your particular
mission? Did you think that economic development could in some way help
the war effort or help the Vietnamese people in any way that the U.S.
was able to?</u>

<u who="#billo">I was pretty jaded. I’ve talked to a lot of Americans who were
in Vietnam early on, in the [President Dwight D.] Eisenhower
administration, and they—that was well before the insurgency had heated
up in the Mekong Delta. And so they felt that they were doing effective
work in helping the South Vietnamese get organized.

But by the time I arrived, you know,—not to state the obvious, but
President Diệm had been assassinated, we had revolving door governments
in Saigon, there’d been a series of prominent attacks by the enemy in
Biên Hòa and Pleiku. [Secretary of Defense Robert S.] McNamara and the
leaders in the Pentagon, for me, had lost credibility. You know,
they—they would decide on an additional tranche of American troops. And
so, you know, at first it was 100,000, and then it was 200,000, and then
ultimately it was 500,000. And so it was hard for me to attach any
serious trust.

Of course, by the time I arrived after ten months of language training,
it was already ’69, and we had more or less smothered the problem with
our presence, both military and civilian, and at some level we’d taken
over the country from the Vietnamese. And then if all went well, of
course, the idea was that America would hand the country back after we’d
repelled the North Vietnamese.

And to top it all off, [President Richard M.] Nixon, [Secretary of
State Henry A.] Kissinger and [Secretary of Defense] Melvin [R.] Laird
took office in early ’69, and they—they had introduced Vietnamization,
which was an actual diminishing of the American military presence.

So you asked me, well, could I see any prospect of what I was doing I
the field having any impact, it was all too late, in my opinion. It
was—no, I couldn’t. So what did I do? Well, I was—my job was in the U.S.
embassy economic office, and my job was to analyze economic developments
in the country, so I wasn’t in the business of building schools or
putting in wells or growing better strains of rice to help the
impoverished folks in the countryside; I was in the business of
analyzing what was going on, putting it on paper and sending it to my—up
the hierarchy.

So I hope I’m answering your questions.</u>

<u who="#dim">Absolutely.</u>

<u who="#billo">The part I didn’t mention was that sometime during my language
training, I took the initiative to seek out the [U.S.] Agency for
International Development, AID folks responsible for Vietnam. And I
persuaded them that I had the credentials and I would soon have the
language training to do economic analysis, and that this turned out to
be one of my more successful moves. So when I arrived in Saigon in
March or April of ’69, I think it was, I was assigned to the joint
embassy AID economic office.

So that—that kind of got me out of the CORDS as an institution, and
ultimately they—just to finish the thought, I—ultimately, in Saigon,
they decided to nominate me as a economic reporting officer, and I would
have joint responsibility to the embassy in Saigon and to the deputy for
CORDS in IV [pronounced Four] Corps, which is in the Mekong Delta
region, who was John Paul Vann.</u>

<u who="#dim">Yeah.</u>

<u who="#billo">And so I had two bosses, and it was cool. I was 25, and people
actually read the things I wrote.

And the other cool and advantageous thing was that I—since I arrived in
’69, it was a quiet period from a military standpoint. The enemy had
shot its bolt in the Tet Offensive, and they needed two years to
regroup, so I was able to travel all over South Vietnam. I never carried
a weapon. I drove frequently. They assigned an International Harvester
Scout, four-wheel drive vehicle, and when I wasn’t driving, I was taking
short hops by aircraft from one location to another. I could drop in on
any given provincial capital and talk to the Americans there or talk to
the rice merchants.

So I’m kind of getting ahead of myself here, but joining the U.S.
embassy economic office was—played to my strengths and gave me a feeling
that I was growing, both intellectually and otherwise. I’m not sure that
I would have had that same outcome if I’d been down in a remote province
or district doing as honorable work, but it was nothing that was in my
background, so—yeah, it was—it was a very, very intense period right
around then.

So I—[Thumbs through some papers.] I was going to show you a document
which I’m not finding, so—oh. [Continues to search.] This is an
organization chart for IV Corps in the Mekong Delta.</u>

<u who="#dim">This is a document that Charlie has just handed to me.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. And it’s dated June of ’69. And so it’s proof positive
that I actually was at this location <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal> and that I had this
title, and these were the colleagues that I dealt with. It was a very
interesting organization. As you can see, it was half military and half
civilian. And so that’s where I learned a lot about dealing with the
U.S. military up close. We kept—we kept very busy, and I felt that I had
some definite responsibility.

And the only other thing that I would say—and here I’m bragging a
little bit—was that I—I developed a reputation in Saigon as a guy who
knew the Mekong Delta, who traveled all over the Delta, who spoke
Vietnamese. There were relatively few Americans who spoke Vietnamese.
And so I became sort of a go-to guy in my little area for visitors
coming out—there were countless visitors in that period. All throughout
the history of our involvement, there were people visiting from
Washington who had been asked by the White House or asked by the NSC
[National Security Council] or asked by somebody to go out and do a
study mission and find out what’s really happening in Vietnam.

So these guys often, occasionally came down to IV Corps, and I would
take them around and expose them to various provincial capitals, and
we’d ride the canals. We’d often—the river obviously plays a prominent
role in the economy, and for a few piasters [Vietnamese currency], one
could engage one of the local fishermen or farmers to take you down the
river to explore around and see what’s going on.

So that became, over time, after I’d been in country for several months
and proven myself—that became—as I said, I became sort of a go-to guy
that people trusted. There were some Americans in Saigon that probably,
if they had their choice, would not have wanted to venture out of the
capital, and it was easier just to stay put.

So the deputy for CORDS was former Colonel John Paul Vann.</u>

<u who="#dim">Wow.</u>

<u who="#billo">He was a civilian when I knew him and, again, a very
controversial figure, and whole books have been written about him. I
fortunately got along with him pretty well. I guess—I don’t know, I must
have done something that he liked, and he sent my reports up a chain of
command. He sent them to the RAND Corporation. And this report here
[presents document] is one I wrote on rice production and marketing in
the Mekong Delta.</u>

<u who="#dim">It’s another document that you’ve handed to me.</u>

<u who="#billo">I just kept a copy. But for anyone who was intensely interested
in how things worked in that society and the role of the Chinese rice
merchants and the critical importance of rice in the Asian diet, this
was a significant document. And the cool thing for me was that I found
out later that some distinguished people at RAND in Santa Monica
[California] had seen my work. So that was exciting.

I only—just to conclude this monologue by saying up until getting to
Vietnam, I’d never really done anything in my life except being a
student, and every youngster, including yourself, is going to face that
day when you leave the ivory tower.

And so that is at least some perspective on why this job I had and this
luck that I enjoyed: landing a good job after the Tet Offensive, working
with smart people and being a civilian, as opposed to an Army guy in
Vietnam—you know, why this was so significant to me that all this came
together after whatever, five or six months in Vietnam.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you. That was a lot that you gave me.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah.</u>

<u who="#dim">Maybe we can backtrack a little bit and piece through it part by
part. So in the document that you gave, as you mentioned, while you were
training, going through language training that you had passed protesters
going to the Pentagon. What was that like? Did they interact with you at
all? What was your perception of them?</u>

<u who="#billo">That’s a tricky question because I had already said I wasn’t a
true believer in what I was engaged in, but I wasn’t going to—for
whatever reason, because of my background or my youth or my upbringing,
I was not going to engage in rabble rousing, and not going to launch
missiles <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal> at people, you know. On the other hand, I was smart
enough to realize that some of the arguments that these antiwar people
were advancing had some—some truth to them.

Yeah, it was—yeah. Of course, socially, on the weekends, you’d go to a
party or go to a bar or something, and people would ask you, “Well, what
are you up to these days?”, you know, and then you’d have to sort of go
through the whole thing about how you were studying Vietnamese. Yeah.

So these—yeah, it was—it was totally foreign to me, any concept of
protesting of this kind. I will say that I was—later on, when the people
were actually—the students were killed at Kent State [University]—</u>

<u who="#dim">Right.</u>

<u who="#billo">That was a riveting thing. I could not believe that students who
were just being students—and even there were some protests, I know, at
Dartmouth in this era—could be fired on by the National Guard! It was
staggering. Yeah. But, I mean, later on, when Nixon came in—</u>

<u who="#dim">In ’69.</u>

<u who="#billo">In ’69, he took office. They started wholesale arrest of
protesters, and they had schemes of buses that were dedicated to—and so
they’d arrest the students, put them on buses and take them to Robert
[F.] Kennedy [Memorial] Stadium in D.C., for processing. You know, Nixon
and people like John [N.] Mitchell, the attorney general were
systematic, you know, in how they dealt with this.

But it was—there was a lot of torment, a lot of stress for me. And
initially, when you’re in a ten-month program, the first couple
months—you know, it’s—there’s no deadlines, you know? You just—but
<vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal> the closer you get to month eight, nine and ten, you know,
suddenly it’s real, and then it becomes _really_ stressful. Like, well,
“What are you gonna wear—get your airline ticket? What stops are you
gonna make to Saigon?” That was—so that was a period of time the whole
country was riven in some level, and I was kind of a
20-something-year-old kid being tossed around in this thing.

Yeah, it was—even to the moment that I was on the plane coming into Tan
Son Nhut Airport [sic; Air Base], I was stressed out, not knowing—and
this is another lesson that one learns—you know, not knowing whether the
plane was going to be shot at or whether there’d be a bomb detonated
that first night—when you read the daily newspaper and you see a
photograph of Saigon and the caption is “VC Rocket Mauls Downtown
Saigon” or “the Port” or something, and you see a photograph, and I used
to in those days think, _My God! If that’s taking place yesterday on
that spot, the whole city must be alive with rockets coming in._
Photographs can be so distorting and so misleading. You could also say,
you know, that those photographs of those protesters at the Pentagon—it
was, like, _Oh, my God! You know, the whole place is coming undone!_ And
it’s nowhere near that. You know, it—anyway, it’s a simply, basic lesson
that—don’t trust what you see in the papers, and don’t trust
photographs.

Because I came in, and I guess someone met me at the airport and we
went to some officers’ billet somewhere or some USAID hotel, and I think
I took a taxi to work the next day. But that whole first few weeks in
Saigon, I was real jittery, you know, because you just never knew—the
city was way overpopulated and so congested and noisy, and motorbikes
and bicycles, automobiles all commingled. Yeah, when you couldn’t be
clear as to who was near you and why, and—you know. So those first few
weeks, until I’d acclimated and figured the situation out, were—yeah,
were trying and stressful. You go—yeah.

As I say, not to repeat, but up till then, I’d never done anything in
my life except be a student, so I had no baseline, and so that’s part of
the sort of learning process, the learning curve.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you

Actually, I’d like—I was wondering if you would be willing to talk
about this letter.</u>

<u who="#billo">Oh.</u>

<u who="#dim">Who this came from and—</u>

<u who="#billo">Right, right, right, right.</u>

<u who="#dim">—explain a little bit for the tape recording.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. This is a copy of a letter from Secretary of State William
P. Rogers to me dated March 7, 1969. He had just been appointed
Secretary of State by Richard Nixon and the final day of our Vietnam
training, our group of whatever it was—20? I can’t remember now; 15,
20?—were invited to a meeting at the office of the Secretary of State,
and it was kind of a morale boosting effort, and it was a laying on of
the hands by the Secretary of State, and “Go get ’em, fellas” and—it
lasted maybe ten minutes, and then we were ushered out.

What happened was I—I had been—this whole notion of going to Vietnam
and being inducted into the CORDS program, for which I felt I had no
affinity for—</u>

<u who="#dim">This is before you went to the AID?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. And even after I went to the AID office, I had no sort of
assurance of what my job was going to be. They talked a good game about
working in the Joint Economic Office, but I—you know. So I left the
Secretary of State’s office, and I was slightly angry or perturbed, and
I went downstairs, and I got access to a typewriter and wrote him a
letter, saying that—I know I was kind of boasting that I’d had all this
graduate training and all this and that, and I didn’t think it was
appropriate for—I thought I’d joined the Foreign Service in order to
serve in our traditional embassies, and I didn’t think it was
appropriate for folks with “this background” to be assigned to what I
called—I think I put in the letter what I called “Peace Corps work.” And
I guess—I didn’t say this, but I guess my point was, if I’d wanted to do
Peace Corps work, I would have applied to the Peace Corps. That was the
unstated message.

So <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal> I went back upstairs to the seventh floor, and I bumped
into this staff aide outside the office, and I said, “I was just in this
meeting with Secretary Rogers, and I didn’t particularly like what was
going on, and I wrote him a letter. Here it is.” And the guy took it!
That was a surprise.

So then a week later, I’m at home, and I get this response from Rogers.
It was just a token response, but he said, “Thank you for your letter of
March 7. I appreciate your frankness.” I guess I must have been pretty
frank. And then he says, “You have my best wishes for your forthcoming
assignment. Sincerely, William P. Rogers.”

So it was, like—on the one hand, he appreciated my frankness; on the
other hand, it was: “You’re goin’ to Vietnam, buddy.” <vocal><desc>Laughs.</desc></vocal> And so I
always—it’s not often one gets a letter from the Secretary of State. I
guess this goes back to something in my father’s training or my family
background, in which he always said, you know, “Tell people the truth.
Tell them what you think.” You know, in his realm it was medicine, and
you’re an intern or you’re in training. You’re standing before a
patient. You know: Don’t waffle around, as an intern, you know? And even
with a most senior person on staff, they honor you if you’re direct and
you don’t sugarcoat things or you don’t—you’re afraid to speak the truth
to power. That was the overall message that I grew up with, you know? So
this was my effort to speak truth to power.

Later on, I learned that the Foreign Service introduced a policy right
after we left, which was that they wouldn't accept anyone for basic
officer training unless those individuals agreed to be assigned to the
CORDS program. So there was no, like, suggestion that you might land a
posting in Buenos Aires or London or Moscow. Yeah. If you agreed to come
to Washington and report for duty, you were going nowhere else but the
CORDS program in Vietnam.

So, you know, this is not proof positive of cause and effect, but, you
know, it’s an association with—who knows? Who knows how these decisions
got made? But I—I always found that—and the older one gets and the more
you read about things like Vietnam and other policy, major policy
decisions, like the U.S. toppling of Saddam Hussein, that if people in
responsibility would just speak their minds and get it out, that the
place will be better off, you know. It always helps if you have a
fallback position when they fire you. I grant you that. You know, it
always helps to have family money or some— take over Dad’s business at
home. Or of people at the top get tired of listening it you speaking
truth to power, it is nice to have a niche to fall back on.

But I was always told, or persuaded, that: “Hey, you know, life’s short.
Just, you know, be direct and”—one of my heroes is Brent Scowcroft, who
owed a lot to—to the Bush family. But, damn it, he was going to tell the
administration what he thought about the idea of going into Iraq. And
he’d burn his bridges with the Bush family. But you have to honor people
like that, who—who put everything on the line and risk—risk a lot for
getting unpopular views. And so that’s another lesson in the Vietnam
exercise.</u>

<u who="#dim">And on the subject of people giving their all in tough situations,
you mentioned briefly the 1968 attack on the U.S. embassy. I was
wondering if you have any things on that.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. During the Tet Offensive, the Viet Cong sent a sapper team
[members of the Viet Cong’s elite C-10 Sapper Battalion] that actually
blew a hole in the outside defensive wall of the embassy, and the VC
were running around in the compound at night, trying to blast through
the front door. There were three Marine guards defending the front door,
and there was a duty officer from the Foreign Service upstairs. He had
the duty for that particular week. He happened to be on duty the night
the VC broke in, and he had to react right away to take steps to defend
the front door of the embassy. And one Marine was—was down, and it
appeared that the Viet Cong had the power to break in, which would have
been a horrific psychological and political effect for America, to have
its own embassy invaded by the enemy.

And there ensued a long battle. The U.S. called in Military Police, who
were working that night in and around the embassy. They were called in
to deal with the Viet Cong. And my colleague, [E.] Allan Wendt, who was
an economist, had to come down and rescue the Marine who was wounded and
drag him onto the elevator, and he had to call the air base in Tan Son
Nhut airport for assistance to evacuate the Marine, and he had to man
the telephone, direct line to Washington, under very, very dangerous
circumstances. He had to speak to the duty officer in Washington and
explain that the embassy was under attack.

After several hours in which the air base at Tan Son Nhut tried to land
a helicopter on the roof to bring in weapons and help and evacuate the
wounded Marine, they finally succeeded in landing, and within an hour
more, the attack was neutralized. This was a very, very ticklish and
dangerous situation.

Allan Wendt had the composure to be credible with the people in
Washington, and he was later given the award for heroism. In another
hour or so, it was daylight. Bodies were lying all over the compound.
The sappers had failed in their mission. General [William C.]
Westmoreland showed up, looking very—very West Point. Directed the
embassy personnel to be back at their office, at their desk, by noon.
I’m very, very emotional about this. [Weeping.] Because Allen Wendt was
my boss. He was a civilian. And I always ask myself, _What would I have
done under similar circumstances, a similar situation if I’d been on
duty that night?_ It was a absolutely critical performance.

And this brings to mind another lesson or fact that’s not widely known.
It’s the risk that U.S. Foreign Service people are under almost every
day of every year in a variety of settings, that is underappreciated and
little understood, and occasionally gets publicity, as when our
ambassador to Libya [J. Christopher Stevens] was killed in Tripoli [sic;
Benghazi] in the last couple of years [on September 12, 2012]. And it’s
not widely known that more Foreign Service officers have been killed in
the line of duty than the U.S. Secret Service, whose role is to defend
the president.

A friend of mine pointed out recently, and I don’t know if this is
factual information, but a Foreign Service colleague of mine told me
that the U.S. Coast Guard has suffered two Coast Guard employees killed
in its recent history—let’s say since—I don’t know the actual period in
question, but let’s just say since World War II. It can be looked up.
And that the number of Foreign Service officers killed in the line of
duty is over a hundred.</u>

<u who="#dim">We’re taking a break. </u>

<incident><desc>Emotional moment in interview.</desc></incident>
<incident><desc>Recording interruption.</desc></incident>

<u who="#dim">All right, so we’re back, and thank you so much, Charlie, for
sharing that story. So with all of this, coming into Vietnam, the ’68
attack, all that’s going on before, how are you preparing entering into
country? What do you do with the family? Was there any sort of talk
amongst other—your other Foreign Service classmates?</u>

<u who="#billo">I was essentially scared and didn’t have the experience to gauge
what I was getting into when I landed in Saigon. I, of course, did talk
to Forest Service colleagues who had come back from Saigon, or I picked
up snippets of info about what it was like. I guess I also knew someone
who worked in the Joint Economic office, who helped me settle in and
answered a lot of my questions.

My family was—I was unmarried, but my parents were pretty stressed out
about the whole prospect, and they probably, at some level—my father
probably said, _Well, it’ll probably do him some good [to] get out
there._ He probably had doubts about my long-range career prospects.

I remember—not to over-personalize this, but I remember telling my
mother that “if things go sour and I get bumped off, don’t let anyone
stand up and say, ‘Charlie Billo was a great patriot and really believed
in what he was doing.’” I didn’t—I didn’t—that was how sort of worried I
was, I guess. And I just—I could not allow that someone would later
stand up and—because I—I was smart enough and well read enough and been
around Washington and New York enough to know that this enterprise in
Vietnam was not looking good and that the more people we put in, the—it
wasn’t doing any good.

And so anyway, I guess that’s an answer to your question. I had a great
support network. You know, I was reviewing this weekend some letters
that I had written home. The family was constantly bombarding me with
letters when I was in Vietnam.

Yeah. I mean, my fraternity brothers at Brown, you know—they were
married, and some of them—one of them had already done Navy OCS, and he
was starting his career, and he was sending me care packages. And so,
yeah, it was—I had good support.

The thing is, and the piece you have to know, is that after a month or
two in Saigon, when there was no enemy action at all, when I was
surrounded by all these highly-trained economists, I realized that—and
this is—I’m somewhat embarrassed to say this, that the embassy people—we
were living in our own little cocoon, and I have to repeat I’m somewhat
embarrassed to say this: We—a typical day, when I was in Saigon, was
work from 9 to 12; 12 to 3, you’re on lunch break. You walk over to the
Cercle Sportif tennis club and swimming pool and grab a tennis game with
your buddies, then have a quick sandwich and come back to the office.

So my so-called service in Vietnam was so different than the average
American that it’s almost embarrassing to relate. And that’s why I want
to make the point that the people who were in the U.S. military and who
were combat officers have nothing but my highest respect for their
bravery and their performance in the jungle, for the hazardous duties,
the chopper pilots, the Medevac people. I have nothing but the highest
respect for their bravery, and I doubt I could have functioned in those
roles.

And so in that framework, I’m embarrassed to have to relate that. We
were—first of all, there were literally thousands of civilians in 1969
in Saigon, and it was such a bizarre environment because these civilians
had to be—had to have housing and had to have food, restaurants. So you
had this effort on the part of the Pentagon and the AID and State to
re-create a little bit of America, and so there were officers’
restaurants on the rooftop gardens of certain high-rise buildings; there
was a PX [post exchange] in Saigon, where one could drive on the weekend
and do your PX shopping for vegetables and meat as well as—</u>

<u who="#dim">What does PX stand for?</u>

<u who="#billo">Post exchange. Every Army base around the world has a post
exchange.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay.</u>

<u who="#billo">And civilians are often given acc- —government civilians have
access to this, so people could be seen leaving the PX, you know, having
purchased their tape recorders and their televisions and their Samsonite
suitcases. Yes, Saigon was a—it was a very surreal environment. [Two
loud mechanical tones.]</u>

<u who="#dim">We’ll be taking a short break.</u>

<incident><desc>Recording interruption.</desc></incident>

<u who="#dim">[Soft mechanical tone.] Okay. We’re back.</u>

<u who="#billo">I was describing the surreal situation in Saigon with the
thousands of Americans there, civilian and military. Kind of a
bureaucratic—[loud mechanical tone]—that had formed up, and how—[a
series of loud mechanical tones]—</u>

<u who="#dim">We’re actually going to stop for today. We’re having minor
technical problems. And we’ll reconvene tomorrow, August 15^th^, 2016.</u>

<incident><desc>Recording interruption.</desc></incident>

<u who="#dim">This is Chileta Dim, and I am in Berry Library, Baker-Berry
Library, in Hanover, New Hampshire. It’s August 15^th^, 11:30, and I’m
here with Charlie Billo.

So thank you again, Charlie, for meeting up with me again. Yesterday we
had to end before we concluded with our interview, and we’re continuing
today. Yesterday we were talking, when we left off, about sort of the
atmosphere in Saigon entering in ’69, when you were beginning your
service, and can you pick up from there?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yes. Let me start out by pointing out that I was present in
Saigon in two installments. The first was in the spring of ’69, as you
just mentioned. Then I was transferred to Can Tho [pronounced TUH], the
regional capital in the Mekong Delta, and I lived there for some ten
months, and then after that, I was brought back to the embassy in
Saigon, due to some policy shifts that the embassy undertook. And the
second installment lasted approximately six or eight months, as I
recall. And I left Vietnam in about October of 1970.

So what I was saying yesterday was that, first of all, Saigon resembled
physically a provincial French town, such as Toulouse: the architecture,
the way the boulevards were laid out, the size of the city. It was quite
a beautiful, small, provincial town, with villas, with shuttered windows
to keep the sun out and protect against the monsoon.

And on top of that, when I arrived in ’69, was this overwhelming
American presence. It was a very congested city, as I said earlier. It
was way over-populated. There were literally thousands of Americans,
including civilians, present. We all needed lodging. We all needed food.
And so then what I saw almost immediately was that the government had
provided most all creature comforts that one could find back in the
States for the American contingent. And so there was this surreal
situation of being in a war zone and yet enjoying restaurants, enjoying
the post exchange, as I mentioned yesterday. The embassy had a swimming
pool, and one was able to circulate by car, at one’s convenience. There
was all sorts of support mechanisms, including access to Stateside
television.

So the image I’m trying to create is this overwhelming, smothering
American presence. In fact, for a lot of different reasons, the U.S. had
to trim back or alter the French Colonial architecture and all, in order
to suit the U.S. military’s needs for heavy transport going through the
city. There was a lot of pollution due to heavy trucks as well as
motorbikes. It was—day to day, it was fairly chaotic.

Now, as an embassy employee, I had the advantage of dedicated housing.
And, as I mentioned, the government rented a number of houses or villas
from the Vietnamese, and we were more or less—in my two installments in
Vietnam, I lived in one of these villas, and we had servants, and we had
guards posted outside.

I’m mentioning this by way of contrast to some of the military officers
and enlisted people, their situation. I met a couple of acquaintances
that I’d had back in the U.S. One of them was posted in Biên Hòa, which
was quite close to Saigon—</u>

<u who="#dim">Do you remember a name?</u>

<u who="#billo">I—I—I will come forth with his name. He’s since deceased.</u>

<u who="#dim">Oh.</u>

<u who="#billo">He invited me up to Biên Hòa, and I saw his—what they called in
those days a “hooch.” It was like a small dormitory room, and each—let’s
say there were ten enlisted men to the dormitory; each one had a locker
like one would have back in school, to hang all their worldly
belongings, and —they probably—they—I don’t remember precisely, but they
may have had bunk beds.

And so that was how a lot of Americans wound up. And so I wanted to draw
the distinction between the seemingly—seeming unfairness of this whole
involvement, where you had folks in Saigon who were—they were nicknamed
the “Saigon warriors,” quote-unquote, and they had many advantages that
they would have had had they never left the United States.

And so there was this sharp divide, which was part and parcel of some of
the tensions involved in a lot of the decision making and approach that
was adopted in prosecuting this war, and I hesitate to even talk about
it because the overwhelming majority of draftees probably, I’m guessing,
never had access to what I—the situation that we enjoyed. And it’s—I
have nothing but respect [weeps] for those people.

I told you yesterday that we typically would break for lunch around noon
and walk over to the Cercle Sportif, which was a tennis and swimming
club that had started in the French Colonial period. It was like
something one would see in a movie about Colonial period: a large
clubhouse with a veranda, a large swimming pool. Oftentimes one would
see the French businessmen who were still in country. A lot of them were
operating the rubber plantations and had investments in the rubber
plantations, and they—they were often Corsicans. They would frequently
show up at the Cercle Sportif. Their children would show up and be
sunbathing by the pool. And we would have a game of tennis, and then, as
I mentioned, grab a sandwich and go back to the office.

This may be a good moment to mention that the lifestyle I’m describing
is one of—Saigon used to be called “the pearl of the Orient.” And it was
a jewel in the French Colonial crown, and the allure of the tropics is
an element that I think is important. I can’t say that I’ve seen much
mention of this in the literature, but I may have missed it. But I
always felt that the allure of Saigon and the lifestyle, the
attractiveness of the people, of the climate explained a lot about the
French presence. And in my—I’m guessing, I’m speculating that it
explained a lot about the number of the foreign correspondents from
France, who stayed on in Saigon for many, many decades: François Sully
and others. It was a very seductive atmosphere.

I would be curious—I’ve talked to colleagues about this. I’ve talked to
U.S. military veterans anecdotally about this, and I always felt that
the atmosphere and the lifestyle of a westerner living in Indochina was
a very, very seductive and important, potentially important matter. I
don’t want to take it any further than that right now.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay. Thank you.

So a little earlier, you mentioned that sort of these American comforts
in Saigon where it was almost a smothering presence and they were almost
pushing out, a bit, the French to make way for these American
lifestyles. Did you at the time view that as odd, or is this—or were you
so caught up in your work that you maybe didn’t take notice of this?</u>

<u who="#billo">The thing about this when I arrived very late in the game, ’69,
was that the U.S. had undergone the big buildup, obviously, militarily,
and they had a similar buildup in terms of civilian officials. And by
the time I got there, money was no object for this war, and so there
were—there were a lot of folks on the civilian side that were hired, and
there were a lot of contractors who were hired because there
was—everyone had his own motives, but I would just say that there was
good money to be made. There was probably better money to be made
working for the AID program than one could get back in the States. There
were—the government was paying the regular salary plus hazardous duty
pay.

So by the time I got there, in many quarters in Saigon there was this
large American presence and offices and high-rise apartments, and so it
don’t—in answering your question, I think I’m trying to describe what I
always wondered about, which was what Saigon and the Mekong Delta looked
like in the ‘50s, after 1955, in the early years, when General [Edward
G.] Lansdale and the support group were there in small numbers, in this
lovely, provincial town that had this wonderful allure of a southern
French city.

It was a question mark I’ve harbored for many, many years. I’ve since
filled in some of those answers, but essentially when I got there in
’69—as I mentioned earlier, the U.S. had wrested the war away from the
South Vietnamese to some degree, to a large degree. And we—we were there
in numbers; we were going to fight the North Vietnamese; we were going
to show the South Vietnamese how to do things in the—in the field.

And so I cited this one example of—this is perhaps just a trivial
anecdote, but I cited the example of how the military, for their own
requirements, had to clear out these wonderful tree-lined boulevards
because oftentimes they would run a convoy right through the center of
town, and they didn’t want to be stopped by overhanging limbs from these
trees.

So I—speaking personally, I found this sort of a shock, but it was a
war, and the military had its motives, and they knew what they were
doing, but that’s just one example of the—there are multiple other
examples of how this U.S., overwhelming numbers eventually interfered
with the operations of the local society.

One other factor which I want to splice in is the elites in Saigon, the
Vietnamese elites—some of the government ministers, some of the
successful importers, businessmen, some of the folks who were well
connected politically or had worked for the French—they still had their
role and their presence, and I knew several Vietnamese who attended a
grammar school or high school that was run in the French way, and it was
called the _Lycée Marie Curie [de Saigon]. It was a school for young
girls._

_And so that was another factor that I—while I on the one hand accept
that liberal democracy is good and it makes room for all kinds of
pluralism, and that’s the difference with the communist system. I always
felt—I wondered on my question whether the U.S. would want to be working
hand in glove with people who were holdovers from the French colonial
period, who represented kind of an elitism._

_Half these folks that I knew and went to Marie Curie didn’t speak
Vietnamese that well, because the instruction was in French. And so
that’s another sort of a piece to a very complicated environment in
Saigon, that—it’s hard to encapsulate everything, but we were—it was a
very amorphous, free-flowing thing, and I—I just wondered whether—and I
think this, later on—we did this the right way. We should throw our hand
in with the peasants and the underrepresented people in the field, out
in the provinces, rather than protecting wealthy people or even being
seen to represent—to protect folks who hardly knew their own native
language and weren’t exactly representative of the country._

_DIM: Thank you._

_So you’re talking a lot about French and American businessmen in the
area, U.S. governmental workers, Vietnamese elites, and you mentioned
near the end about your liking this idea of throwing your hat in with
the peasants, with the underrepresented populations. I was wondering if
you can talk a bit more about your relationship with the Vietnamese
people in Saigon, in a non-working fashion._

_BILLO: Well, I can’t say all that much, unfortunately, except I will
note—and this may sound like bragging, but I spoke pretty good
Vietnamese, and <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal> one of the fantastic benefits for a westerner
who spoke their language was that the man or person on the street would
light up immediately when you exchanged pleasantries with them in their
own language and in a credible, intelligible way. So I—I took great
satisfaction in that. I enjoyed the banter. The South Vietnamese were
very friendly, by and large open, happy people._

_And I—I think I did some good things in actually getting to know them,
using the Vietnamese I had. And it was reciprocated, as I said, in that
they made me feel like a VIP every time I used my Vietnamese. I don’t
know why they did that except they probably—I’m guessing that in the
French Colonial period they never heard or they rarely heard a westerner
who would bother to speak their language. That’s the only possible
explanation I could come up with._

_But I—to be honest, most of my contacts and friends with the
Vietnamese society were through work. I had the benefit of a couple of
local Vietnamese advisers, I guess they were, who did a lot of the
legwork for us in the economic section, and outstanding people who were
willing to go to work for the Americans, even though—who knows, after
the U.S. departed, what happened to these individuals._

_But by “legwork” I mean—we would perform price surveys in the local
market. We would send a Vietnamese, one of our advisers, down to the
market to ask the daily rate for rice or the daily rate for fish. It’s
something that an outsider could never have done because you wouldn’t
get any accurate data. And so—_

_And we had a lot of what the embassy called “local hired employees,”
who basically did support work for us in the building. You know, they
would—they were the ones who typed up our reports. I got along really
well with those folks, again maybe because they heard me speak
Vietnamese; they thought I was an acceptable, good guy. [His voice
cracks.] I don’t know what happened to a lot of those people. Some of
them made it to the States. I know that. The embassy got them out in
’75._

_One of them was sent to—<pause/>—I found out later one of them was
sent to a communist reeducation camp multiple times. I mention that
because if anyone thought that the U.S. had made a mistake trying to
defend liberal democracy in Vietnam, they’re dead wrong. We may have
executed the job in a terrible way, and a lot of mistakes. But anyone
who knows anything about these reeducation camps that were instituted
after 1975 will know that this was serious business._

_So I’m kind of strained from the subject. But since I was mentioning
my colleagues in the office, at the Joint Economic Office, I might just
remind people that this was the pre-digital era, pre-Internet, and the
most we had was an IBM [International Business Machines Corporation]
electric typewriters. There was a lot of use of carbon copies._

_And another facet which I know has already been discussed in various
places, like the Class of ’64 volume on Vietnam that the difficulty of
people deployed in Vietnam to contact their families back home—kind of
by today’s standards, pre-email—it was very primitive, and I vividly
remember soldiers on the weekends in Saigon going to I believe it was
probably the USO [United Service Organizations] office, which was a
support office for the military in Saigon, and them queuing up to get
ten minutes of a phone link to America and have a brief chat with their
spouse or their children. That was just another element that I want to
insert here to describe the times, in effect. We’re talking here the
’60s and ’70s._

_And so, yeah, that was very vividly etched in my mind. I mean, since
you had asked me about the atmosphere in Saigon: The weekends, one would
see enlisted men who were in Saigon for a couple nights’ R&amp;R [rest and
recuperation] leave probably—I’m not sure where they came in from,
probably nearby provinces, I’m guessing, maybe from_ Biên Hòa. And that
was a whole eye opener because (a) by ’69 we were—we had announced we
were Vietnamizing the war or the U.S. was scaling back, taking people
out, so the morale on the U.S. side was not the greatest.

And these folks were coming into Saigon on R&amp;R, looking for a party,
and I was probably—I was an observer and saw a slice of what was
happening out there and that I’d never otherwise would have seen. It
gave me a real insight or piece of the puzzle that I didn’t see day to
day. These folks were working the bars, and that culture has been well
documented in various films, and I’m not going to elaborate on that.
But, again, it was part of the—part of the mosaic in Saigon.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you, Charlie. So I think you gave me a really clear
description of what Saigon was like in ’69, and so maybe we’ll pivot a
little bit and talk more about your day-to-day work. You mentioned
yesterday that the bureaucracy that you were involved with involved both
military and civilians, so I was wondering if you could a little bit
about what it was like to work with actual military men.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, I’d like to do that. In my training course in Washington
and when I got to Vietnam, the CORDS program had identified the
top-of-the-line majors and lieutenant colonels in the Army and had
decided that these were the people that were needed at the province
level, to be province senior advisers. I got to know some of these
people, and they indeed were very able. I mean, some of them were West
Point grads. I mean, these are people that were so able, they’d been
promoted at a very young age to major. They were occasionally lieutenant
colonels, as I said. And they were no-nonsense, they were well educated,
and I really respected those people.

Of course, in any large organization, including on the civilian side,
there are echelons of people who—as I said earlier, who are present for
their own motivation or their own goals, and some are more able than
others. But I—I—I have a mixed kind of a take on the U.S. military. And
I think, you know, up until, say, ’66, ’67, when the CORDS program was
getting underway and they decided they needed to find these very, very
qualified personnel, that—my reading tells me that the Army had adopted
a more traditional approach and that there was a lot of careerism and a
lot of filling in reports that would advance one’s career.

And the thing that I want to point out—and maybe this is not the best
place to point [it] out—was that—is that this war was intended or
viewed, early on, in ’63, ’64, as this was going to be a “cakewalk.” My
sense, from my reading, is that in many ways, the U.S. Army—and I may be
being unfair here, but that they—maybe the U.S. military in general
wanted to get into this. After all, it was—it was a—you were—you were
operating in a developing country. You’re up against people wearing
black pajamas. You represented the world’s superpower. Hey, how could
this possibly—how could they possibly hope to take us on?

And besides, my take is that the military—it was an opportunity for
promotions. Every time there’s a shooting war—I’m now talking—I don’t
know if this is true today, but in the ‘60s, when there’s a war on,
that’s when the military is at its, quote-unquote “best.” And by golly,
captains are going to get promoted to majors, et cetera, et cetera. And
that’s—hey, that’s an advantage, too. So it was very, very complicated.

<pause/> The other thing—and this is somewhat related—was the—I think
the Army has, by the nature of the business, has its own rigidities, and
we were talking yesterday about the failure to speak truth to power. In
a hierarchical organization like the U.S. Army—and I never was in it—I
don’t think there’s a whole lot of space for contradicting the colonel
if you value your career.

Now, that may have changed. But by rigidities I mean an addition
[_sic_; admitting] that counterinsurgency warfare in Vietnam did not pan
out the way we thought it was going to be. So any neutral observer would
have said—I mean, this is all documented in the Pentagon Papers, that it
didn’t work out. Any neutral observer would say, “Hey, let’s—we’re back
home now. Let’s do an after-action, comprehensive study of what
happened, what went wrong, where we made mistakes and are we going to
prosecute the next counterinsurgency.”

To my utter astonishment [weeps], at the time of the decision to go
into Iraq to topple Saddam Hussein, I read or heard that there was no
such analysis available on the shelf that was a comprehensive study of
how to conduct a counterinsurgency war and lessons learned from the
Vietnam experience. If David [H.] Petraeus had the brilliance and the
insight to initiate such a document—and from what I’ve read, during the
Iraq involvement he required a systematic review of what happened in the
past in Vietnam and lessons learned and how we got to do this
successfully.

And so you asked me what I thought, working next to the U.S. military.
Those are some anecdotes. I had some great contacts. When I lived in the
delta with people of varying ranks, from captain up to lieutenant
general, smart people, able, the best we’ve got, but there’s a tendency
in big organizations, including the civilian side, to group think, and
organizations like the various branches of the military, don’t have a
lot of room for people who question authority. And the best leaders, in
my opinion, are people like David Petraeus and others—I’m not going to
try to list them—who have a sense that something’s not right, and they
have to ask questions and go back against their leaders and commanders,
even if it’s not career enhancing.

That’s all I’m going to say.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you.

So maybe we’ll move on. You gave me a slight chronology of your time in
country. So you were in Saigon for six to eight months, then ten months
in Can Tho, and then you were back in Saigon, so maybe we can begin with
your first period in Saigon. What were you doing? Who were you working
with? And just sort of what was your general, day-to-day working
experience?</u>

<u who="#billo">Right. That’s very good. It was a memorable period. I told you
yesterday I reported to Allan Wendt,—</u>

<u who="#dim">Yes.</u>

<u who="#billo">—who was branch chief in the market analysis division. And my
first few weeks and months were spent in familiarizing myself with
Saigon, with the country, with the office routine, and it ended up that
I was asked to go to IV Corps, the headquarters in Can Tho, to replace a
very able AID officer named Lee Jones. Lee now lives in Rutland,
Vermont, and is a part-time professor at Boston University. Lee Jones
was one of those individuals who was dedicated to solving economic
problems, who had worked in the developing countries, especially in Laos
and did some good work there, who volunteered for employment in Saigon
because he wanted to test his analytical abilities in a setting like
Vietnam. And so he was—he was a, you know, interesting individual.

As I say, he asked to go to Vietnam. He did a great job. He was
energetic and creative, and he—he was the best that the AID had. For a
lot of different reasons, he wanted to transfer back to Saigon, I think
for family reasons, and the office in Saigon was only too happy to have
him come back because of his drive and creativity. So I replaced Lee in
Can Tho.

But those first few months in Saigon, I think it was a question of me
getting my feet on the ground and the office reviewing their whole array
of employees and seeing where I could best fit in and what their overall
needs were. So there’s really not much to report.

I did make a couple of trips outside of Saigon, to the provinces,
memorable trips. The idea was for me to get—get acquainted with the
Mekong Delta region and then for later on, for Lee Jones to introduce me
around to some of his contacts, be they Vietnamese or American.

I should mention that if we weren’t driving the roads, typically we
were flying in some very, very fancy Swiss-made aircraft that were used
by the Swiss in the Alps. They were, as a lot of folks know—the airline
was called Air America. It was a CIA [Central Intelligence Agency]
“company, and the aircraft were STOL, short takeoff and landing aircraft
that one could land in the Alps on a glacier successfully and then take
off with a very brief run of a couple hundred yards and they were up and
gone. So in war zone, these aircraft—and especially with the jungle of
Vietnam and Laos, these aircraft were a wonderful instrument.

They only carried, like, four, five, six people max. One simply had to
get one’s name on the roster the day before if one was planning a trip
to one of the provinces. And one would show up, jump in the Pilatus
[PC-6] Porter, and they’d whisk you off to whatever province you wanted
to visit. It was—that’s how I—it’s what I remember from those two
initial familiarization trips I made in those first months in Saigon.

So just to reiterate, when I was there, money was no object, and almost
any sensible idea that one had was achievable. And the other thing that
one should point out is that because it was a shooting war, there was a
lot of scope—not everyone wanted to—not every American wanted to be
involved in a shooting war, so people like Lee Jones or Charlie Billo
show up, the system is not going to say, “Oh, what have you done in the
past? Let me see—let me look for some gray hair,” you know, as you might
expect from a corporation back in the States, where you have to have a
résumé a mile long. In a war zone, young people are given
responsibility, and there was heady stuff. It took me a while to realize
this process after I arrived in Saigon as this rather green and untested
and fearful young man.

I gradually was able to shock all of that and realized that it
was—there was an opportunity. They wanted you to do a job, and no one
was asking, “Well, what are your connections, and what have you done on
your career?” and blah, blah, blah. Just: “You, you and you, get out
there.” It was a very, very enabling experience, and there was a lot of
luck involved in being in the right place at the right time.

And, as I said yesterday, there was a lull in the fighting. I only had
one what I called a dangerous or hairy experience in my two years I was
there. And so it just shows that (a) in a fighting situation there’s all
kinds of opportunity for young people to make their mark, and (b)
there’s a whole lot of luck involved in almost any pursuit that you
develop. And there’s just no accounting for—for luck. But I’m conscious
of that in my—in my two years working in Vietnam.</u>

<u who="#dim">We’ll be taking a short break.</u>


<incident><desc>Recording interruption.</desc></incident>


<u who="#dim">Okay, so we’re back after a short, one-minute break. And thank you
so much for talking about your first couple of months in Saigon,
Charlie. And so now, after you’ve explained sort of how you were
learning on the job, you were cutting your teeth those first couple of
months in Saigon, and you described how you got your job in Can Tho. I
was wondering if you can begin with when did you get to Can Tho, and
what was the town like? What sort of place was it in comparison to
Saigon?</u>

<u who="#billo">My recollection is I probably transferred to Can Tho in about
June of 1969. And Can Tho was a one-horse town. It happened to be the
regional headquarters city for the Mekong area, and the CORDS program
had a major presence there. AID had a low-rise apartment building for
civilian employees. Across the street was an officers’ mess with a
guard. All of these buildings had guards out front.

And so one typically would go across the street to get breakfast or
dinner from that low-rise building. And I remember there was a beer
factory on the main drag, not far from where I lived. It was called
Brasseries [et] Glacières d’Indochinois [sic; d’indochine]. They
produced 33 Beer, which—anyone who lived in Vietnam in those days knew
what 33 Beer was. It was an export lager, developed by the French and
probably available throughout Indochina in the Colonial era.

I took up residence in Can Tho. I was nominally—I had a Vietnamese
counterpart, who was, as I recall, a colonel in the Vietnamese army, a
wonderful guy. Smart. Had an attractive wife. A good family man. And I
believe his title was inspector for the IV Corps region in the
Vietnamese government structure.</u>

<u who="#dim">Do you remember a name?</u>

<u who="#billo">I can’t come up with it right off the top of my head.

So I told you yesterday my immediate boss in Can Tho was John Vann. My
day-to-day job was to, when I wasn’t traveling to various provinces, to
look into warehouses owned by the Chinese rice network, to check on
inventories. I was engaged in a lot of briefings at headquarters. We had
monthly meetings, where the provincial senior advisers would come to
town. John Vann and, later on, William [E.] Colby, head of CORDS and
later, after that, director of CIA, would conduct briefings for the
province senior advisers.

And we had a string of visitors. As I mentioned yesterday, part of my
job was to escort visitors. There was no end of people coming out of
Harvard or coming out of Washington agencies who wanted to get a
first-hand glimpse of how things were going in Vietnam and offer their
advice to players in Washington, in the White House or wherever.

So I was essentially my own boss. I wasn’t getting any directives from
John Vann. Occasionally, the folks back in the Joint Economic Office
would ask me to travel to a certain province and check on something, but
I was, you know, 25 years old and my own boss, access to a vehicle to
drive around, access to these wonderful aircraft that I talked about. It
was dramatic stuff. It would surely beat being a graduate student in New
York City, which is <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal> the simple way of saying that it was a
very inspiring period, and I—

So I—among other trips I made, I visited the Cà Mau Peninsula, which
was as far south as you can go in Vietnam. It was a scene of a
long-standing VC insurgency. Later on, the U.S. military, to stop this
insurgency, engaged in defoliation. The VC, because it was largely a
swamp area with estuaries and mangrove—the VC found it a relative safe
haven, and the U.S. military wanted to defoliate the mangrove swamps to
expose the enemy.

I met—I remember on this familiarization trip to Cà Mau, we met a Navy
SEAL team [U.S. Navy's Sea, Air and Land Teams] that was operating on
the Swift Boats [Patrol Craft Fast (PCF)] in those estuaries and got a
glimpse of some of the aid programs that were in operation there, the
schools and health facilities that the aid program was building. I
remember when we went to talk to the SEAL team guys, they were pretty
tough individuals. It was an impressive group.

So, yeah, getting back to my job, I had to learn an awful lot about
rice agriculture, and as a city boy, it was a steep learning curve. I
had to learn the difference between paddy rice and milled rice, and I
had to know the growing seasons and the weather issues, and I had to
know what provinces produced the best rice and who controlled the
distribution system: where was it warehoused before it was shipped to
Saigon?

And the reason this was important was that because of the critical
nature of rice in the Asian diet, if there was a crop failure, the
shortfall would have to be filled by imported rice, and the AID had a
program all in place to bring in shiploads of U.S. rice from—typically
from the West Coast, California rice, because the transport was easier.

But to make that all happen, you needed to figure it out with a lead
time of three months in order to load the ships and get them into the
ports in Saigon, so we, in the market analysis division, submitted a—I’m
going to say a biweekly report. I can’t remember how often, but—on the
rice situation in country. And so I was a link in this reporting system.
I was the guy who had to make a first-hand observation of inventories
and let the people back in my office in Saigon know what the stocks
looked like, and they would in turn make an estimate how many boatloads
of American rice should come in.

So, yeah, what I should digress and mention is that the Mekong is one
of the top five or six rice-producing areas in the world. Because of the
nature of the landscape and the paddy fields, it was a natural place.
One could toss seeds into this landscape, and anything would grow
because the temperature was right, the water levels were good, and the
rains helped.

And so this is not often treated in the books that I’ve read, but there
is a real dichotomy between North Vietnam and South Vietnam. South
Vietnam was the rice basket and in a good year could produce more rice
than was needed locally, after they deducted for seed purposes. That
left rice for consumption, and there was a surplus, and that could in
one way tied back to North Vietnam’s efforts to gain control of the
south.

I don’t want to overstate that, but in the mountains of North Vietnam,
it actually snows from time to time, and one thing that I want to point
out here is that because of the climate in North Vietnam and other
factors, the populace had a different approach than in the Mekong Delta,
where—we used to say that the peasant sin the Mekong Delta, because of
the food surplus, were kind of fat and happy, not just the rice growers
but the fishermen. Life was easy, from a survival point of view, whereas
in the north, it was—the landscape and the climate was more forbidding.

And this—it’s well known, and I don’t know if it’s widely written
about, but the North Vietnamese have a more aggressive personality as a
group, for some of these reasons that I’m mentioning, that they are more
aggressive, they’re tougher, because of climate and other factors, the
need to eke out survival, subsistence. And I have to say that in
choosing <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>, as we did to defend South Vietnam, it had to be
factored in that the folks we were working with side by side were not as
driving and unforgiving as the North Vietnamese.

And one—one in Washington should know or have known this dichotomy, and
I’ll very quickly say that the people in the Foreign Service, like
myself, who had worked in Italy, saw the amazing similarities between
Italy and Vietnam, that it’s well known that the people in Milan and in
the north—Milan, Turin, are much more able, energetic business
people—I’m generalizing—than people in southern Italy. And it was—had
its counterpart, in my opinion, in Vietnam.

You know, there are other analogies between Italy and Vietnam, one
being the rather peninsular nature of the two countries. But you had a
topography in northern Italy which consisted of the Alps, and a rougher
climate than in southern Italy. I don’t want to overstate this, but it’s
an interesting—it’s an interesting factor to consider.

So, okay, yeah, I wrote these reports about the rice situation. I stuck
my head in a lot of warehouses, watched people loading and unloading
bags of local rice. I drank brandy with the Chinese rice merchants, and
then one of the enjoyable things was showing these distinguished
visitors around that region. Professor Arthur—[weeps]—Professor Arthur
Smithies, from the Harvard economics department—we took him out to the
Vietnamese border with Cambodia. And we took people from the Institute
of [sic; for] Defense Analyses in Washington on familiarization trips.

It was—it was very good. John Vann allowed me to use his helicopter
when he wasn’t using it, and that is an experience in itself. I went out
to, as I said, the Cambodian border. A helicopter used to inspect the
transport system from Can Tho north to Saigon because of the two
branches of the river and the ferryboats, backups. Was easy to inspect
them from air.

And I just want to mention, before I move on here: I told you that
William Colby talked to us one day, and one thing I remember him saying
was that—this was in ’69, mind you, a little bit late in the day—but he
said he understands that the U.S. people in Vietnam often refer to our
host government and population as “gooks.” And he said [weeps], “I’m
layin’ down the law here, now that no one is to use that epithet.” And,
of course, there were other ones, too, like “slopes” and you name it. I
mean, we had—“we”—I mean civilians and military alike had derogatory
epithets.

Colby was a little late in the game. Apparently, a gook was actually an
expression coming out of the Korean War. It had to do with the Korean
language, so it was just transposed to any—a derogatory expression for
it would do for almost any Asian because these people were not like us,
and they were people to be belittled, and so that’s what I got to say
about this.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you. Well, that might be a nice segue into just talking
about what it was like working with these big-name guys. Colby
eventually, as you said, would head the CIA. Paul Vann is a very famous
person. What was it like interacting with them on a daily basis? Like,
they were your direct bosses.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. I had relatively little interaction with William Colby. He
was way, way above me. I remember the obvious things that people comment
about he had these sort of thick eyeglasses, and he was a rather
slender, athletic man, but people always compared him to the television
show, _Mister Peepers_, just because of his physical feature. But he was
a highly decorated [weeps] OSS operative. And he’d had multiple tours in
Vietnam, so this guy knew what he was talking about.

As for John Vann, he was colorful and decisive, no nonsense. You don’t
waste his time with a lot of preliminary war stories. It’s get in and
get out. He was brave. He would go on night patrols in the districts and
accompany Vietnamese military patrols. He’d fly in. He was known for
arriving in a province unannounced, just to see what was going on and
not give the American senior adviser an opportunity to put on a show. He
was tough.

Fortunately, I got along with him. I’m not sure why, but he came from a
redneck Virginia family, and he wore blue jeans and short-sleeved
shirts, and we all knew that he’d left the Army as a lieutenant colonel
and then recycled back to Vietnam as a civilian at a very high level.
And we’d all read about him because he gave interviews to David
Halberstam of _The New York Times_ and [Cornelius M.] “Neil” Sheehan.
And he’d created a nice kind of aura around him of bravery and military
savvy, and dedication to the job in Vietnam. So that was at one level.

Of course, one later read Neil Sheehan’s book, _A Bright Shining
Lie[:John_ _Paul Vann and America in Vietnam]_, that unearthed a lot of
information that kind of pulled the rug out from under John Vann, and
that there was a lot of deception and that he was a womanizer. He
actually was on the brink of a court martial, and so he only had one
option, which was to leave the Army. But that only came out much later.

And then he was killed, flying his helicopter up in—I believe it was II
Corps [pronounced Two Corps].</u>

<u who="#dim">II Corps is where?</u>

<u who="#billo">That’s two-thirds of the way up the peninsula. And he had a
premature death, but he was trying to rally the Vietnamese commanders in
that area that were facing an attack by the North Vietnamese, and his
helicopter went down. I don’t remember the precise details.

But I do <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>—getting back to Can Tho, I do remember some of the
Vietnamese employees, womenfolk, telling off the record that John Vann
was a womanizer. And, you know, that was good information to have, and
it didn’t necessarily surprise me. And so when I read Neil Sheehan’s
book, I said, _Well, okay, we knew that._ <vocal><desc>Laughs.</desc></vocal>

And so that’s as much as I can say. I—I—I liked John Vann. He supported
me, as I said yesterday. He went all out for me. He got my name in front
of some people in the States, and he let me use his helicopter? What can
I say? He was—he was active, and he was tough.</u>

<u who="#dim">You mentioned female Vietnamese employees, so I was wondering if we
could transition to how you interacted with these Vietnamese farmers
that you were working with, your contacts in Can Tho, and maybe a little
later we can talk a bit about what it was like working with Chinese
merchants.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. One didn’t work with Vietnamese peasants and rice farmers.
One talked to them anecdotally or one drove past them on the dirt roads
and observed them. But the point to be made is that in my estimation,
and I think books back this up, that the rice farmers and the peasants
in general in South Vietnam weren’t—they were apolitical. They, in my
estimation, weren’t terribly interested in the South Vietnamese
government versus the VC. They wanted to be left alone and to do what
their families had been doing for millennia, which was grow rice. These
people were not educated people. They were hard workers, and they could
be seen wading around in the rice paddies, and so that’s what I have to
say about that.

So I was dealing more with the better educated, commercial folks who
then collected the rice from these paddies, and then they ran mills. I
remember visiting a lot of rice mills.</u>

<u who="#dim">Owned by Vietnamese.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, right. At that time, they were owned by probably Chinese,
what they called the “overseas Chinese” that had lived in Southeast Asia
for—for centuries. Yeah, so I would go into these mills. I’d observe
what was going [on], and the manager would show me around. As a visiting
American, I guess they had to show you around and pretend to be happy to
see you and, you know, make a good effort for you, and have a cup of tea
together.

And then there was this other crew of Chinese merchants, who controlled
the warehouses. The bags of milled rice then would go into warehouses
that were immense structures, and all these bags would be loaded by
peasants who would have—these bags probably weighed a couple hundred
pounds, and you’d see a guy loading the bag on his shoulder and walking
up some gangplank and tossing the bag onto a pile. It was—it was
different.

But you could tell that these Chinese rice merchants were kind of more
entrepreneurial and mercenary. They had the big houses with the
television antenna on the roof and lots of picture windows and a couple
of nice cars parked out in front. They were different, and they probably
in turn had their counterparts in Saigon. And actually the section in
Saigon called Cholon [pronounced cho-LUN], which means “big market,” the
market side of the city. And so somehow these bags of rice I’m talking
about were put on trucks and trucked to Saigon and wound up in the
Cholon warehouses for distribution and sale in Saigon.

I don’t have much to say about the guys I told you I drank brandy with?
I mean, it was, like,—again, I was the American visitor. They had to be
polite and welcoming. We got kind of—you know, I was doing my best to
hold my liquor, and I tried to glean info from these people about what
was going on. Yeah, it was—

So that’s really—that’s as much as I can say. But they—I want to make
the point that there was a network for rice distribution, and it was
carefully controlled by the Chinese. And we got this knowledge about
this network through the advisers that I mentioned earlier, who—locals
who spoke Chi- —one guy in particular, Peter Kao [pronounced like cow],
K-a-o,—</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you.</u>

<u who="#billo">—who spoke Chinese, and he did our legwork. And he developed much
of the info that we had about who was running this show and how it
worked.</u>

<u who="#dim">Can you talk a little bit about how it did work? So what were these
networks doing? Were they just controlling the rice? Were they
controlling distribution?</u>

<u who="#billo">I guess—well, two things. One was that the motives of these
networks was to drive the price of rice up as high as it could, so they
obviously would buy as cheaply as they could from the people at the
paddy level, and then by withholding rice from the market in Saigon,
they would hope to then come forward and get the best price at the last
minute. And what they were up against, though, was the Vietnamese
government was aware of these people and could exercise their control to
some degree in preventing this kind of distortion taking place.

The government also bought a sizeable amount of rice on a fixed contract
basis, so that gave these individuals—they could count on the Vietnamese
government—South Vietnamese government to buy a good portion of the crop
early on. But, of course, the last thing that these merchants wanted was
to trigger imports from America. That would undercut their situation, so
it was a double-edged situation.

The one thing that I haven’t pointed out is that the Vietnamese had a
taste preference for their local rice, and not all American, not all
rice coming out of America met their preferences in terms of the degree
of hardness of the rice or the length of the grain and the lack of
aroma. These were clearly—it’s a fairly obvious statement that there was
a strong preference for locally grown rice.

So that’s about as much as I can say. I didn’t comment on—I think you
and I had been talking earlier about—the one dangerous moment I had in
this job was I flew out to Châu Đốc [pronounced chow duk] Province [now
An Giang Province, Vietnam] for one of these talks with the provincial
team, and I was supposed to stay overnight. And to Châu Đốc Province was
along the Cambodian border, and it was not the most secure area.
<vocal><desc>Chuckles.</desc></vocal> So all was good.

And then they assigned me to some dormitory for the night, and around—it
must have been around two in the morning, I hear this loud knock on the
door, and one of the American hosts says, “Get up, get up! We’re under
attack!” And I—of course, you’ve been sound asleep, and it’s in the
middle of the night, and you’re sort of groggy, and the last thing you
want to hear is, “Oh, shoot, we’re under attack!” And he says, “Follow
me! Follow me!”

And we were then herded into this concrete, large concrete bunker that
held, let’s say, eight or ten Americans, and it had—like most bunkers,
it had some series of small slits on all corners. And you could hear
small arm[s] fire in the distance, and it was pitch black. It was the
middle of the night. And I guess <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>—so they issued me an M1
carbine, which was not exactly the weapon I was talking about yesterday,
the M16. It was a World War II, Korean War carbine.

And they said, “Okay, poke that out there. If you see anything moving,
shoot!” And I’m saying to myself, _God! Here I am, this dude out of
Columbia University, been in country only six or eight months. Is this
what I signed on for, you know?_ I mean, I was—I was not—I was not
happy. These other guys were a little bit more calm, and they were doing
the same thing on their side of the bunker.

Shortly thereafter, you could hear helicopters patrolling, and what
happened then, the small arms fire kind of drifted away, and the guys in
the bunker said, “Well, it looks like the VC are pulling back. The
choppers must have neutralized them.” You know, by then it was probably
five in the morning, you know, and everyone’s breathing a sigh of
relief.

But I just remember them saying afterwards that they almost forgot about
me, that they were all in the bunker, and some guy says <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>,
“Hey, what about that guy from Can Tho, the visitor? Where the hell is
he?” <vocal><desc>Chuckles.</desc></vocal> It was in that way that the other person came and
knocked on the door.

That was—in two years in the country, that was the only nerve-wracking,
crazy experience that I had. The rest of the time, I just traveled
around without any weapon. And maybe in hindsight, maybe stupidly
traveled around like that? But when you’re in your 20s, you do a lot of
stupid things you later on would question.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay. Thank you.

So you described the rice situation very well. Just a small question:
Did you sense any contention between Chinese—well, as you describe,
Chinese merchants who were sort of hoarding rice to inflate prices and
the farmers who were actually growing the price [sic] and having to buy
rice at this inflated price?</u>

<u who="#billo">I can’t remember any tension along those lines. I mean, it’s a
different economy, a different society, a different level of economic
development. I don’t recall that the farmers were well organized the way
you would expect, say, in a more developed country. So I don’t recall
that the farmers had any leverage in the situation. In the French days
and the millennia before that, there were individuals called
“ramasseur”, whose job was to go from farm to farm and collect the paddy
and—so that’s what I remember. You’re dealing with a society that was
not an advanced society, so—

I would only add that there probably was ethnic resentment against the
Chinese merchants, who were a little more clever and a little more
organized. I know the Vietnamese had epithets that they used to label
the Chinese, so that’s probably where the tensions came—you know, like,
it’s a natural phenomenon if there are people that you feel are
exploiting you and they’re some other ethnic background or something.
It’s easy to assign epithets to these people. But that’s—I think that’s
the best answer I have to that one.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay. Thank you.

And you mentioned—or you were talking about your visits—I was also just
wondering: Was there a particular visit, a particular visitor that
really sticks out to you in any particular way? And you mentioned that a
lot of them were sort of experts in their field and they would give you
advice. Did you find that advice helpful?</u>

<u who="#billo">They weren’t giving _me_ advice. They were getting a quick
snapshot of ground truth in Vietnam. Of course, in my recollection, 90
percent of these visitors were people who supported the war, so they—and
probably people in the government, in the administration were only too
happy to have those people go out, make an in-person assessment, and
that’s what they were doing. And then they would write it up when they
got home or go and talk to their contact person in the administration
and add another degree of knowledge about what was going on.

Yeah, I mean, and a person like a Harvard professor in that era of ’69
would have been in a definite minority on the campus, but that was the
kind of personality this man had, of not doing the group think thing,
not doing the easy thing, which was to join the antiwar movement or—</u>

<u who="#dim">“This man” is?</u>

<u who="#billo">Arthur Smithies. I’m just picking him as one example.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mm-hm.</u>

<u who="#billo">So he—and he had the common sense and the savvy to say, “I’m not
going to sit here in Cambridge, imagining what’s happening in—I’m going
to go out there and actually go to the field and take some risks and get
a first-hand experience, and then when maybe I’m back in Cambridge I can
talk to my colleagues in the faculty club and say, “Hey, wait a minute.
You know, I was just there.” And so that was what that was all about.

I had people from the Bureau of the Budget [now Office of Management and
Budget] and others. I’d like to think I had some outstanding person from
Washington, but I would just <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>—I would just say that I—I will
tell you I had some support from people in the RAND Corporation who had
read some of my work, and they—</u>

<u who="#dim">And do you have any names?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, I will mention one person, who I admired, who was Charles
A. Cooper. He later became the minister-counselor for economic affairs
at the embassy. He volunteered. He worked in Washington for a long time
under Robert Komer. He was a brilliant person, who had already had a
tour in Vietnam earlier, in the economic side of the house, and—I never
showed him around the delta, but it was probably the sexiest moment I
had in the two years in the sense that he sought me out. He wanted my
opinion about things. And he gave me some inside information about the
fact that he was probably going to come back to Saigon and that there
was unhappiness with the existing policy in Washington, and they were
going to make some changes because the present team was on the wrong
path economically. And so that was—that was nice, to be courted like
that. That was—that was unforgettable.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mmm.</u>

<u who="#billo">I’ll just mention very quickly that the existing leadership in
the economic side in both State and [US] AID had bought into an idea of
austerity and imposing economic austerity on the country. That was when
they—I guess they just felt that the U.S. was spending too much money
and it was a wasteful expense and that the idea was to tighten down on a
lot of the programs and the monetary flow.

It had some adverse—some immediate adverse effects because they
eliminated overtime for the local Vietnamese employees, of which the
embassy had hundreds, of drivers and support people. And suddenly the
word was out that these drivers, who were trying to support their
families, could not longer get overtime pay. And so people—there was
violence as a side effect. The drivers found out or got the word. The
boss had say, “Hey, drivers, no more overtime,” so they went and
retaliated against that guy. So that was just a small example of an
overall picture which was trying to pinch pennies. And probably these
gentlemen were well motivated. There was a lot of waste, and they
needed—

That was when they drew me back to Saigon from Can Tho because they
said, “Why are we wasting money supporting an observer out in the Mekong
Delta? You know, we can save—we don’t need those people out there. Bring
’em back.” And so I was summoned back to Saigon.

What I’m trying to finish up by saying is that—and this was in 1970—that
this policy of austerity ran against the grain with the Nixon
administration and what they were trying to do, and the recommendation
was made to Henry Kissinger to have a change of leadership at the
highest levels in the embassy, economic section. That was pretty big
stuff. I mean, seriously big stuff.

Of course, Nixon was on a track, and Kissinger was on the track of a
gradual tapering down of our presence, as is well known, prolonging it
over a three- or four-year-period in the hopes of diverting or stopping
a huge, cataclysmic, score-settling thing in the United States as
between those who thought we were doing good in Vietnam and the
sacrifice of our soldiers had been—had to be accounted for, versus the
other people, the antiwar group, who said that “the sooner we get out,
the better. We’ve already lost too many people.”

So Kissinger’s strategy was to prolong this over a longer—a four-year
period. And who knows? The idea was that maybe our allies in South
Vietnam would, over a long period of four years, prove themselves
capable of standing up to the North Vietnamese challenge. So that’s a
hotly debated question, the wisdom of that.

But I was in just one small corner of the whole question, and I—I was
nearing the end of my tour in Vietnam, and it was a privilege to be in
on a lot of these questions and to know people [weeps] such as Charles
A. Cooper and others, who knew what the right questions was. That was
always the first thing. If you don’t know what the right questions are,
you’re not going to come up with any good answers. That’s all I have to
say on that one.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you, Charlie.

So you say you were recalled from Can Tho because of this new policy of
austerity in 1970.</u>

<u who="#billo">Right.</u>

<u who="#dim">Do you have about a month when that happens?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, I think it was—oh, my gosh! That was in the spring of 1970
sometime.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay.</u>

<u who="#billo"><vocal><desc>Laughs.</desc></vocal> I remember Charles Cooper coming up and sitting down
with me and a couple of other guys, like Allan Wendt. And he said, “I
hear you’ve been brought back from Can Tho.” He said, “I hear you worked
for John Paul Vann.” I said, “Yeah, I lived there for ten months, and
now I’m back.” And these guys sort of looked at each other and said—the
body language was: “Whoa! That might not be the best decision to be
making, you know, as we’re trying to right this ship.” But I just—it was
just one anecdote.

Okay. So what—yeah. Okay, so what did I do when I was in this period in
Saigon? I was getting ready to leave the country in October, and I
continued to make trips, forays to the delta by plane to check on the
usual rice problem. I flew to other parts of Vietnam, South Vietnam,
such as Da Nang and Huế, to talk to American advisers there.

I do remember—I think I mentioned yesterday that I had to escort
newcomers to the embassy. These were people that would be taking my
place, and I had to familiarize them with the job, and we did a lot of
traveling and a lot of boat excursions and whatnot on the Mekong River.
It was—yeah, I—I can’t say that I—

Oh, I remember one time in this period. My boss asked me to be an
interpreter in French between the U.S. Army and some French rubber
plantation owners. He, my boss, spoke good French, but he had other,
more pressing things to do, so I went out to the plantation that was,
let’s say, an hour from Saigon. I don’t remember.

Sat down. The U.S. Army had—there was some issue about compensation or
something. I can’t remember the details. There were two U.S. Army guys
and a couple of French guys, and someone owed money for something. Maybe
the U.S. had damaged part of the plantation. <vocal><desc>Chuckles.</desc></vocal>

So that—yeah, I wasn’t quite as—maybe not quite as busy in this period
in Saigon as I had been earlier. Yeah. I mean, the building I was in in
this period was called USAID 1, and it was a high-rise building. It was
like a honeycomb of offices and AID personnel next to Foreign Service,
State Department personnel. So we had our own little mini-bureaucracy:
lots of meetings and—

I do remember the day that I left. I was saying—I’d packed my bags. I
booked on a flight out of there. And I was saying my goodbyes to my
superiors in the office, and they were sitting around the table, talking
about—as I stood up to shake hands and all that, someone used the word
“experience.” And I shook hands and was headed to the door, and I heard
the boss say, “Well, there goes our experience right out the door.”
Okay, it was a throw-away remark, but, you know, it was—for me, it was
sweet music to my ears, that maybe I had some, made some impact in those
two years and that I—so that was—getting on the plane to leave, it was
pretty satisfying to think about that.</u>

<u who="#dim">Yeah. Thank you. Yeah, so that must have been a very emotional
experience for you, October of ’70, going back home after two years of
service in Vietnam.

You brought this document along with you dated also in October of 1970,
and I was wondering if you could just explain for us a little bit about
what it means, why you brought it.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yes. It’s a letter from the minister of economics, Pham Kim Ngoc
[pronounced fahm keem nyup], who incidentally was an Oxford
[University]-educated economist. I’m not sure where he is today or
whether he’s still living. But it was, I think, a gesture to recognize
some of my work and some of my activities when I was in the Can Tho
office. Given the date, he must have been aware that I had left the
country, and he was giving me a nice send-off, where he says, “I wish to
thank you for your devotion and your contribution to the economic
welfare of my country.”

And it was very interesting. I remember, speaking of the minister of
economics, going over to his office one time with my boss and sitting
down—and this gets back to that story I was telling you about austerity
policies—and there was a lot of corruption in Vietnam, as you know, and
people needed licenses to do business, and the one way to get licenses
was to probably bribe the right government official.

And this gentleman, Pham Kim Ngoc, said, “You know”—he was talking about
having to deal with these American leaders, the two gentlemen who were
promoting the austerity policy, and he said, “In my job as minister,
every day I deal with whores, whores, whores: people seeking a contract
or attempting some subterfuge to get business.” And then he says, “And
then these two American senior officials walk in, who were, like, the
other end of a spectrum, trying to tell me that I need more austerity
and I need to clamp down on corruption and, you know, I need to tighten
up my ship.” He was kind of laughing, you know, because he says, “My
typical day is I’m just confronted with corrupt individuals right, left
and center. And then these guys come in out of the blue and lecture me
in the other direction.” He thought it was kind of a ironic situation.
But—yeah. I think South Vietnam had some very able, able people, and
Pham Kim Ngoc was one of them.</u>

<u who="#dim">Can you spell Ngoc for us?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, N-g-o-c.

But I think over all I would say that there are two schools of thought
about our involvement in Vietnam. One, the orthodox school is the one
that most of these books about the war say that it was a big mistake
right from the get-go, and the U.S. never should have put their big toe
into those waters.

And I belong to the other school, which is the revisionist school, which
lately there have been several well-documented books written about this,
that the war, according to the revisionist school—was that it was a
noble cause but executed foolishly. That’s where I come out on this
thing. I think in the early days, in the late ’50s, when Gen. Lansdale
was there, it was easy to identify qualified, dedicated, patriotic South
Vietnamese leaders, and a lot of times the U.S. gravitated—later on,
there was a tendency to gravitate towards people who—Vietnamese who
spoke good English, you know? If you—it’s kind of bizarre, but you—it’s
just easier to work with people if you’re able to communicate well, so
any Vietnamese that came forward that spoke really good English was way
up there in the esteem of American advisers. That doesn’t always get you
the best—best results, unfortunately, but that’s the way—that’s the way
life is.

Yeah, it was—there were other things that hampered our performance there
over all, speaking historically. The typical military tour was only one
year, and just about the time an officer in the military was figuring
out how the place worked, they were already counting the days to return
to the United States. That, I think, hampered what we were doing. But
there were a lot of other questions that just put us on the wrong path
back in—talking now from ’63 onward.

LBJ was a very insecure individual and a control freak, and he wanted to
be involved in minute detail of everything to do with the war, and he
was totally influenced by some of the New Frontiersmen, the people left
over from the Kennedy administration, such as McGeorge Bundy and Robert
McNamara. And unfortunately, some of those people, as brilliant as they
were, such as McGeorge Bundy—they were the type of egos that they were
individuals who didn’t know what they didn’t know. They were brilliant
analysts, but if they started with the wrong input, they would maybe
come out with the wrong output.

So I don’t know to what extent you want me to comment on my overall take
after my experience in Vietnam. I kind of brought you up to the day I
walked out of the office in October of 1970, so let me know what you
want me to—how you want me to finish this up.</u>

<u who="#dim">Yes, I definitely do want to hear what you think of the war now
that you’ve gone through it. Maybe I’ll give you a couple of questions—</u>

<u who="#billo">Yup.</u>

<u who="#dim">—to sort of structure your thoughts. So you mentioned earlier in
our interview that you knew, and then some other people sort of come to
the conclusion that counterinsurgency didn’t really work out in Vietnam,
and I was wondering: Where do you place your own work in that frame of
counterinsurgency? And did you think what _you_ were doing was
effective?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, I’d have to say, in my own corner of the operation, that if
my work helped drive decisions in Saigon about bringing in American rice
to compensate for a shortfall in the local production and let’s say that
prevented potential rice riots that could have led to kind of political
unrest, yeah, I have to say I thought my work was useful, to that
extent.

You know, there are other little insights, like the one I mentioned,
where only people who had been through the Vietnam language program
would understand that there were significant ethnic differences between
the northerners and the southerners—you know, could make that kind of an
observation.

It turned out that—yeah. So—otherwise, my corner of this
counterinsurgency game was the economics of the corner, and most of the
writing in the books you read never touch on this, so that—that was a
unique niche, and it drove a lot of things. And there were a whole bunch
of other smart people who have written about these types of things. I
remember reading something recently, written in ’64, if I remember
correctly, by a visitor to Vietnam, that pointed out the U.S. <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>
was flush with money, with dollars, and Asia was flush with people, so
the question is: How can we deploy what _we_ did best (which was our
wealth) and avoid falling into a trap against what Asia did best, which
was deploy just thousands upon thousands of fighters? You know, that
was—that was a key—an interesting way to analyze the situation. And I
think that we had to do more to boost morale in the south through our
economic resources and not try to Americanize this war by sending in
more and more troops, because that’s not what we did best.

The other thing was—I haven’t talked about the Hồ Chí Minh trail because
it’s not part of my portfolio and I really don’t have any—my work had
nothing to do with the resupply of the Vietnamese, the Viet Cong via—by
way of the Hồ Chí Minh trail, but later on, if you want, we can talk
about that.

What were you asking me a second ago about? Oh, yeah, how my work
related to counterinsurgency.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mmm.</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, counterinsurgency—I will just say the obvious—involves the
full spectrum of things, not just military but social and political and
economic, so I think what I did, even though it’s not maybe that sexy,
played into the economic piece of that. That’s as much as I can say.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay. Thank you.

And I also want to just sort of talk a little bit about—you can take
this anywhere that you want—your relationship with your family while you
were in Vietnam. You mentioned earlier that you sent letters back and
forth and that there was quite a few. Did you feel that your family was
particularly worried about you or did they sort of view this more as
another job that might have, you know, different implications but didn’t
see you quite as a soldier? How did they see you?</u>

<u who="#billo">Oh, I think initially they were worried, and then over time—I
wrote them letters, say, every couple of weeks, because I knew they—they
wanted to hear from me. They wanted something. In those days, it was all
snail mail. By the time I’d been there a few months and I was describing
my coworkers and describing my routine and getting more and more
enthusiastic about what I was involved with, et cetera, et cetera,
they—I think they must have had a big sigh of relief.

I also went—took a week off and went home to attend my sister’s wedding
so that my—that was after I’d been in country for, oh, let’s say, five
or six months.</u>

<u who="#dim">So it’s still ’69.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. So they were happy to see that I was alive and well.</u>

<u who="#dim">Yeah.</u>

<u who="#billo">It’s one of those jobs that you do when you’re a bachelor, you
know, and you’re footloose and you don’t even think about your own
mortality. You know, you can do anything. So, yeah, it was—and I told
you yesterday I had a lot of support. I had people sending me care
packages. Yeah, so—</u>

<u who="#dim">So. Thank you.

So how old were you when you left country, 26?</u>

<u who="#billo">Let me—so if I left in—yeah, I probably was more like 27.</u>

<u who="#dim">Twenty-seven. And what did you do immediately after your service?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, I stayed in the Foreign Service and was assigned to work in
the Milan, Italy. And I went almost right away into Italian language
training for four months, I believe it was. And I—we had a small
consulate in Milan, and I was—I was swimming in those waters. It was fun
to be back in Italy, where I’d been as an exchange student. I did find
it hard to adjust to—this was a more traditional Foreign Service
assignment than what I’d been involved with, and it was—it was—I had to
follow the book more and do the routine stuff, so that—that was kind of
a shock to the system, to be frank about it.

I then met my future wife, who was a British woman working at the
American International School [American School of Milan?]. We were
married in June of 1973. The work wasn’t so interesting, but life had
its compensations, and I also got to know the U.S. ambassador to Italy,
Graham [A.] Martin, who was a protégé of Kissinger’s. And Graham Martin
eventually went to Saigon from Rome and was present in the final days of
the U.S. evacuation from Vietnam. He was an interesting character in his
own right.

While I worked in Italy, I received a notice from the department to pack
my toothbrush because I was on a list of individuals who would be going
back to Vietnam to supervise the implementation of the Paris Peace
Treaty [sic; Paris Peace Accords]. That was a little bit of a surprise
in that by then I was engaged to be married and had the wedding all
planned out. And they had a hundred names on this list, a lot of the
guys that I’d studied Vietnamese with. And at the end of the day, they
took the first 50 names off the list and sent those people to Vietnam,
and I—my name was not among the 50. I don’t know why, but I wasn’t going
to fight it, because of the personal plans I had and because I told you
in the beginning that I didn’t see this thing turning out right. And so
that—in the end, it was academic. They didn’t invite me to go back, and
that was it.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay. And maybe we can talk a little bit more about when you were
in Vietnam. So you went to Italy straightaway. You didn’t go back to the
States at all?</u>

<u who="#billo">No, I studied Italian in Washington. The Foreign Service, to my
mind, had an excellent language program. That’s one of their strong
suits. So, yeah, I went—I went home for Christmas and had some leave,
then reported back to the State Department and started the Italian
language training. That must have been in January. I can’t remember
right now.</u>

<u who="#dim">Of ’71.</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah. Yeah. The whole thing about working in Vietnam in that era
in the Foreign Service was that that was a posting that everyone was
talking about, and I had colleagues in the economic section that
volunteered to go there, thinking that down the road, because of the
significance of our presence in Vietnam, the Cold War, blah, blah, blah,
_it’s going to be important to my career to say that I was there, and
I’ll be able to tell war stories, and it’ll_—you know. So <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal>
there was some of this same—some of that attitude must have rubbed off
on me. I didn’t volunteer, by any means, but there was this feeling of,
hey, there were those of us that were there, and there were those of us
that weren’t, you know? And so we like to—my colleagues and myself, you
know, would like to get together and tell war stories and this and that
and the other thing.

But that had little to do with the traditional work of the Foreign
Service, which was a lot more structured and a lot more bureaucratic and
a lot more conservative and traditional. But—</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay.

So you talked a little bit about immediately coming back home and what
that was like, being back with other Foreign Service workers who were
involved in the war, in various aspects. So—and you’re getting married.
You got married in ’73, correct?</u>

<u who="#billo">That’s right.</u>

<u who="#dim">And so what was your feeling when Saigon eventually fell a couple
of years later, after going through a big of your life and getting this,
as you said, more structured, bureaucratic job in Italy? What was that
like?</u>

<u who="#billo">I guess I was pretty disturbed by the images. As you know, there
have been several documentaries about those final days.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mm-hm.</u>

<u who="#billo">And I knew a couple of fellow officers who deliberately flew back
to Saigon to find their in-country colleagues—</u>

<u who="#dim">Mm-hm.</u>

<u who="#billo">—to help get them out of there. I didn’t—I didn’t do that. I
guess—for whatever reason, I—I guess I—I won’t try to justify or explain
that. I just [loud beep], but I—I was disturbed that after all those
years, this is what [a softer beep] it came down to, this chaos at the
gates of the U.S. mission, and people trying to climb on the
helicopters. I mean, what a—to me, it was, like [loud beep]—it was very
disturbing and, like, the lowest point of a series of events [low beep]
over six or eight or more years that were extremely negative [loud
beep], low events. So that’s as much as I can say. It was the lowest of
the low, and [soft beep]—
</u>

<incident><desc>Recording interruption.</desc></incident>


<u who="#dim">This is Chileta Dim, and I’m with Charlie Billo. It’s August
15^th^, 2015. We’re coming back from our previous recording, same day.
We had some technical difficulties, so we had to stop for a few minutes.
So we’ll pick up where we left off.

You were describing your emotions and sort of what you were going
through as the fall of Saigon was happening. Is there anything else
you’d like to add to that?</u>

<u who="#billo">Well, it was a sense of watching these images of the South
Vietnamese trying to escape and get on helicopters out of the city, and
always then running through your mind, _Do I know any of those people?
What about my coworkers there? Where do they stand?_ You know, then
later on, of course, one heard stories about those last few days and the
lack of preparation and the poor execution of the evacuation plan and
whatnot, which I don’t really want to get into.

Some of my coworkers successfully made it out through the good offices
of some Americans working in the Joint Economic Office, and some didn’t.
And I mentioned earlier this one woman who I found out much later had
been sent to a reeducation camp by the North Vietnamese.

But one’s overall take was, _My gosh, couldn’t this whole episode of our
entanglement with Vietnam—couldn’t this have been handled better?_ And
then one does meet people today who make the argument that Kissinger and
Nixon were on the right path and that even in ’73, ’74 there was a
chance to right this ship, but the U.S. Congress withheld budgetary
support with which we could have resupplied the South Vietnamese Army
and refitted the South Vietnamese Air Force. And there were schemes that
some people were running to go around the U.S. Congress and get money
from the Saudi Arabians to fill this resource gap.

And so, yeah, there’s an active bunch of people who think that the
overall situation could have been saved and the chaotic retreats by the
South Vietnamese Army in II Corps and people, military people
taking—throwing away their uniforms and whole cities of civilian
Vietnamese clogging the roads in panic was [an] avoidable thing. But
I—overall—

I remember, on a different note, some of my close high school friends
that I bumped into wanted to hear about my experiences, and then there
became—by then, in 1975, Americans by and large had reached a saturation
point on Vietnam. I remember a good friend of mine saying—he’d been
discussing the Vietnam War for so many years that he was Vietnam’d out.
He didn’t have anything more to say <vocal><desc>chuckles</desc></vocal> or any more questions to
be asked. I guess that was probably true for a lot of—a big chunk of the
population.

But I’ve done a lot of reading lately about the overall strategy and our
failure to execute a viable strategy, and so I think that there were—I
will just say one more time that it was a noble cause foolishly
executed, is where I come out, because the backdrop you need to
understand is the backdrop of the Cold War and the U.S. foreign policy
decisions and the decision makers I the ’50s and ’60s and ’70s. They
were living in the context of the Cold War. The tensions with the Soviet
Union in a lot of hot spots, like Berlin, the conundrum of Mao’s [Mao
Zedong’s] China.

So I would argue that a lot of bizarre and nonsensical decisions were
made in the foreign policy arena, and a lot of crazy things happened.
But you can only understand it in the context of the overall obsession
that the U.S. had with the threat from the Soviet Union. And so the
early days of our build-up in Vietnam, starting with the Kennedy
administration into the Johnson, have to be viewed in this context.

We all know this history, and we all know some of the decisions that
Johnson made, you know, were taken out of— these decisions were made
with the backdrop knowledge about the Republican charge against the
Democrats of “Who lost China?” And I will leave my remarks—limit them to
that because we all know how that uneasiness on the part of LBJ led to
some of his overreaching and ill-advised decisions to execute this war
in Indochina.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you.

So you’ve gone a little bit about your opinions on the war after it’s
happened, and you’ve done a lot of research about it and sort of
situating experience in that, and so just some chronology of your life
after the war. I know you’re a career serviceman. You worked as a
consultant in the intelligence community from ’91 to 2000, I believe?</u>

<u who="#billo">That’s right, I did.</u>

<u who="#dim">Yeah. And now you live up here, in the Upper Valley, and you
volunteer with Dartmouth as a retiree. What final lessons do you have
from Vietnam? Do you think about it in your day to day?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yes, I have to say I think about it, as you can tell from this
interview that we’ve had. It was a very critical time in my personal
development, and it was certainly exciting. It was a lot different from
having a, quote-unquote, “desk job.” But I—I came away with some basic
conclusions about our foreign policy-making apparatus and about
Washington politics and big organizations.

One of the things that has come out in my recent reading about the
Vietnam War was the contrast between Eisenhower’s recommendations about
this war versus the policies of Kennedy and McNamara and Johnson, et
cetera, and—but there’s so much to say, really, about the role of
ethnocentrism and hubris, the idea that “this is going to be a
cakewalk,” and they were discussing in ’63 how we’d get this done by
’65, and the unwillingness of these decision makers, like McNamara and
others, to pay any attention to input from lower-ranking military and
civilians who’d actually lived in Vietnam, who actually knew something
about the culture and the nuances of the scene in Asia.

So what I want to say is that the much maligned Dwight D. Eisenhower,
who was more or less belittled and ridiculed by the incoming New
Frontiersmen—it turns out, from what I’ve read, that he, because of his
experience in warfare and running big operations and living overseas and
dealing with the Allies from other cultures, he had this instinctive
knowledge that the McNamara policy of a slow squeeze and gradual
response was totally wrongheaded and that anyone who knew anything,
especially about the North Vietnamese, knew that they were rigid and
unforgiving and not at all disposed to respond to any political gestures
by the West, especially by the United States.

So Eisenhower, when asked by Johnson and McNamara, et cetera, for his
advice, he said, “Go for the head of the snake.” This is all
well-documented information. Eisenhower—his advice was solicited by LBJ,
and he spent several hours explaining what he thought should be done.
Unfortunately—this would have been in about 1965, if I remember
correctly—unfortunately, even though they called Eisenhower in to the
White House, they then ignored his advice and proceeded with this
graduated response, what McNamara called “the slow squeeze” until
eventually the north was just going to give up and say, “Okay, you win.”

And so that, to me, is critical. The thing is that, as I said earlier,
if individuals have such little experience in these types of
undertakings like warfare, that people like McGeorge Bundy and McNamara,
who, to my knowledge, had never served in the military—they—they don’t
bring to the table anything useful, in my opinion, even as brilliant as
they were in an analytical sense.

And, of course, this is all key and critical now as the U.S. continues
to be a leader in foreign—in foreign affairs and is involved in
engagements in Iraq and Afghanistan and elsewhere, that this capacity to
bring in the right consultants and advisers is—is absolutely critical.

I think—I’m just—yeah, the other—one other question that’s come up
lately in the revisionists’ school I referred to is whether the U.S.—if
you went to attack the head of the snake, whether choking off the Hồ Chí
Minh trail was a potentially feasible thing to do and whether that could
have turned the tide there in 1964 or ’65, when North Vietnam began to
funnel in more and more personnel and supplies—it’s an unprovable
question, but from what I’ve read, Johnson was too timid about going for
the head of the snake, that he feared China would react and send troops
south.

And we didn’t have good intelligence of what the Chinese were doing. And
it’s been pointed out that China, in contrast to the conventional
wisdom, had already sent troops into North Vietnam, doing jobs there
that enabled the North Vietnamese to send an expeditionary force down
the Hồ Chí Minh trail.

So this is something that ought to be investigated further, but I would
just conclude by saying that there was this fear of going for the head
of the snake. It was rooted in the possibility of another—a comparable
thing to what happened in Korea, when the Chinese came over the border
in North Korea, and therefore it was the critical context in which
Johnson and McNamara continued on a kind of a losing trajectory of slow
squeeze, which led to the U.S. putting in 500,000 troops to take over
the fight, which led to the South Vietnamese being bumped out of the
picture.

And so I just—I’ve learned that you want to have as your advisers people
who actually have this kind of experience that I was talking about, and
you also have to find the right ones, like David Petraeus and others in
the Army, who know how to articulate these views and articulate their
experience under very high-pressure situations.

So that’s a long-winded answer, but—<pause/>

I do remember Robert McNamara in his book—I think it was called _The
Reckoning_, saying, among other things, that there was no one at his
level with whom he could discuss Vietnamese affairs, who had a
background or knowledge about Vietnam. And to me, that was the most kind
of absurd and damning remark because I think it’s incumbent upon the top
people to look around and locate those people, no matter how lowly they
might be, and ask them for their input and ask them to tell them what
they’re doing wrong. It takes a certain type of person to do that, and
you have to—I guess you have to be always aware, when you’re in the
White House or in the State Department or wherever, at the top, that
there’s a hothouse atmosphere that leads to a lot of yes men and a lot
of group think, and sometimes things can go off the rails.

So unless you have some other question, I guess I would also say I
noticed—you mentioned that I was a consultant to the intelligence
community.</u>

<u who="#dim">Mm-hm.</u>

<u who="#billo">There were some mistakes made in the intelligence community, on
the analytical side. Again, the same principle holds, that you—you have
to have experienced people in the room who know what the right questions
are and who have the background knowledge and whatever linguistic skills
or on-the-ground experience to pose the right questions. And you—it
takes strong people to run against the bureaucratic safety. And so we
got into a lot of—a lot of thickets by people not—not inviting people
into the room who’d actually been there and done something.</u>

<u who="#dim">Okay. Thank you.

I was going to ask this, but you sort of answered this question: sort of
how your Vietnam experienced your work and how you approached your
career. I just want to end on an observation: You _are_ very well read
about the Vietnam War and what the arguments are out there, and I was
just wondering: Has this research looking into the war—is that a recent
phenomenon, or is that something that has been pretty steady since
coming back? And why?</u>

<u who="#billo">Yeah, that’s a good question. I have always been a Vietnam junky
ever since I came back, (a) because it’s unique experience and not
everybody—my contemporaries had; and (b) I knew—I knew the players. I
knew the names. I knew the locations. So right from early on, I was
reading almost every serious book that came out about that war. And I
read the Pentagon Papers, of course, back in the day. That was going
back to ’75 or something.

And I must say—I’ve got to say when I was invited to participate in the
Dartmouth Vietnam Project, I began reading again because I wanted to be
somewhat credible about this material, and—of course, there’s so much
available in hard copy and on the Internet.

So I’ve—I feel like I have an excellent handle on understanding things,
and I’ve enjoyed—I’ve benefited from individuals like Rufus [C.]
Phillips [III], who published a book fairly recently and talked about
the Lansdale period. And I’ve also been reading books by authors of the
revisionists’ school.

I should sit in on some classes at Dartmouth and find out what young
people in the classroom are asking and thinking about this whole era,
the whole question of our Vietnam experience and what it did to our
country.

I kind of lost the train of thought of what I was going to say.
But—yeah, I guess one final remark I’ll make is that one of the best
films that I remember on the Vietnam War is _The Deer Hunter_, which
was—it’s quite an old film now. But it essentially portrays 18-year-old
American guys coming out of a steel town in Pennsylvania and
volunteering to join the Army to get out of this rather confining place
in Pennsylvania and stumbling into Indochina and a foreign culture and
environment that they couldn’t possibly comprehend from where they came
from in this small town.

And I will only conclude by saying my life story is in some ways similar
in that I came out of a very protected and privileged background, not
knowing a whole lot about the world, especially Asia, and stumbled into
this place called Vietnam and did the best I could. And stumbled out
again. And that’s—anyone who’s seen that movie, _The Deer Hunter_, will
know what I’m talking about, that people signing on to something on
which they were totally unprepared. And, you know, in some ways that was
my experience, but I was lucky.

It’s kind of as much as I can say, that I came out of it and was lucky
to get out of it in reasonably good shape.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you, Mr. Billo. I think that will conclude our interview. Let
me just say I really appreciate you coming down and talking with me, and
we will close this out. Again, it is August 15^th^, 2015. I am Chileta
Din. Thank you.</u>

<u who="#billo">Thank you very much.</u>

<u who="#dim">Thank you.</u>


</body>
</text>
</TEI>
